<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Christian's journal, or, Brief directions for devotion and conversation</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 174 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A32896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3956</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R43093</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">26785150</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 26785150</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109796</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A32896)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109796)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1713:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Christian's journal, or, Brief directions for devotion and conversation</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 336 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Author and sold by R. Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [10]</note>
                  <note>Running title: A Christian's diary.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109796:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A <hi>Chriſtian's Journal<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> OR Brief Directions FOR DEVOTION AND CONVERSATION.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Brevis Praedicatio, longa Comminatio, Actio perpetua.</l>
               <l>Denique quid verbis opus eſt, ſpecte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur agendo?</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed for the Author and ſold by <hi>R. Bentley</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-ſtreet.</hi> 1684.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:109796:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109796:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable The LADY <hi>PHILIPPA MOH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>N,</hi> Baroneſs of <hi>Oakhampton.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Humbly preſent to your La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſhip theſe few Gleanings, which I have gather'd and ty'd up into this
<pb facs="tcp:109796:3"/> little Sheaf. <hi>I</hi> am not aſham'd to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that much of it is none of my own: In Divinity, all men muſt be Borrowers; and no man knows more, than what is Reveal'd; the Ambition of Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, has been one of the chiefeſt grounds of thoſe many Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Schiſms, with which the World is at this day over-run, and the Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided.
<pb facs="tcp:109796:3"/> And to me 'tis no great wonder, when men diſpute Wiſdom with their Maker; when ſoaring Wits will not ſtoop and ſubmit to the plain Truths of the Goſpel, but think themſelves able to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Scripture, and find out more New, and Eaſie wayes to Heaven, than our bleſſed Saviour, or his Apoſtles, have ever
<pb facs="tcp:109796:4"/> inform'd the World of; that ſo many Wander, and Miſcarry.</p>
            <p>You have here, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſet down the thoughts of ſeveral Learned Divines, upon the ſame Subject; Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Rules, from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Hands, directing our Practice; and yet all of them ſo Weighty, as I doubt not but your Ladyſhip will confeſs, few of them could have well
<pb facs="tcp:109796:4"/> been omitted: You will find men, of different Opinions here, All conſenting to further Holyneſs of Life.</p>
            <p>It is the miſchief, Madam, of our Days, that men are too much of a Party in Religion; and regard not ſo much what is ſaid, as who is the Preacher: So that 'tis as dangerous to quote <hi>Charnock,</hi> or <hi>Owen</hi> in the Pulppit
<pb facs="tcp:109796:5"/> as <hi>Mead,</hi> or <hi>Sander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> in a Meeting. This, Madam, is one Reaſon why <hi>I</hi> conceal Mens names; that the Reader may be no way byaſs'd by them: And <hi>I</hi> have indeavour'd ſo to mingle different Parties, that 'twill not be very eaſie to diſcern the Biſhop from the Doctor, or the Coat from the Caſſock; that ſo men, that are ſet up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Quarrels, may Fight
<pb facs="tcp:109796:5"/> in the dark, where 'tis odds they miſtake their man. And this, Madam, is the only excuſe <hi>I</hi> have, for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my ſelf in the Croud of your Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers; among whom you have not,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
               <signed>A more Real humble Servant.</signed>
               <dateline>Covent Garden, <date>Sept. 15. 1683.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:109796:6"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <list>
               <item>P. 31. l. 13. for a, r. as.</item>
               <item>P. 51. l. 5, 6. r. Imaginations.</item>
               <item>P. 54. l. 20. No Comma after Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining.</item>
               <item>P. 74. l. 5. for your, r. Our.</item>
               <item>P. 86. l. 1. blot out the.</item>
               <item>P. 89. l. 9. for to, r. by,</item>
               <item>P. 95. l. 18. r. with.</item>
               <item>P. 100. l. 18. r. delight moſt.</item>
               <item>P. 121. l. 7. for thy, r. the.</item>
               <item>P. 134. l. 2. for all, r. ill.</item>
               <item>P. 139. l. 6. for Neither, r. Never.</item>
               <item>P. 180. l. 14. No Comma after in.</item>
               <item>P. 243. l. 13. r. bring us that.</item>
               <item>P. 246. l. 17. for bat. r. that.</item>
               <item>P. 258. l. 5. no Comma after beſt.</item>
               <item>P. 280. penult. for knoweſt. r. kneweſt.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:109796:6"/>
            <div type="introduction">
               <head>CAP. I. Introduction.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 1.</head>
                  <p>THE beſt way to pleaſe God, the neareſt, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and to get a chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Heart in the mean time till we come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is to walk with God in all Uprightneſs, to live by Faith, which is to frame our Life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of God revealed in his Word. This God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands to <hi>Abraham, Gen.</hi>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:109796:7"/> 17.1. <hi>I am God all-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, walk thou before me, and be thou upright<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>:</hi> This is commended to us by a Cloud of Examples; of <hi>Enoch, Noah, Job, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Zacharias,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Then a Man is ſaid to walk with God, when he daily goes on to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of his Sins paſt, when he believes in Chriſt for Pardon, and believes his Word for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection; when he ſets God before him, and walks always as in his preſence; not after the Fleſh, but Spirit; not <hi>to the will of Man, but God.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>Sect. 2.</head>
                  <p>Everyday is a little
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:109796:7"/> Life, bound with the Night and Morning, as with Birth and Death: one Day is the Brief of the whole; and the whole, but a Day re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated. A good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian firſt turns himſelf to God, by Prayer alone, then with his Family, then to his Calling, to his Society, Eating and drinking, and at Night returns ro his reſt; in all theſe walking Godly, Soberly, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly. This is the ſum of Life, and of the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Manual, wherein Directions are offered for each of theſe particulars,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109796:8"/> which may not be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their uſe, eſpecially to ſuch who are not bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter provided.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How to begin each Day.</head>
               <p>IN the Morning when you awake, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom your ſelf to think on God; or ſomething in order to his Service; let thy fiſt thoughts be for Him, who made the Night for Reſt, and the Day for Travel; who has given thee reſt, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved thee while thou ſlept, and renews his loving kindneſs to thee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109796:8"/> every morning; thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge the Mercies thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and earneſtly pray for thoſe thou ſtandeſt in need of. Prayer is the beſt Key to open the Morning, and the ſureſt Bar to ſhut up all at Night. A Heart early perfumed with Gods preſence, will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of him all the day after.</p>
               <p>Ariſe as early, as the neceſſity of thy Body or Mind will permit; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Example of our Bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.2. <hi>Matth.</hi> 1.35. This Practice will be for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109796:9"/> the Health of thy Body, for the advantage of thy Spiritual and Temporal eſtate; hereby thou wilt have the day before thee, and gain the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſeaſon, and large Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of time, for the exerciſe of Religion, and works of thy Calling: beſides, thou wilt be more able and active for any employment. Too much Sleep hurts the Brain, dulls the Wit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairs the Memory, and makes a man more ſloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; like the Drunkard who becomes more dry, through exceſs.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:109796:9"/>
               <p>The time betwixt your waking and ariſing may profitably be employed in occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Meditation.</p>
               <p>While your Body is dreſſing, (not with effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate Curioſity, nor yet with rude Neglect) let your Mind addreſſ her ſelf to her enſuing Task, bethink what is to be done, and in what order: and becauſe eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day thou ſhalt ſurely be aſſaulted by the World, the Fleſh, and the Devil, fail not to put on thy Spiritual Armour,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:109796:10"/> preſcribed <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6. from the 12. to 18. that thou mayeſt be able to reſiſt. Conſider what temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thy Buſineſs or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany are moſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lay thee open to the day following, and Arm thy ſelf with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution againſt them: And again, what occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions of doing Service to God, or Good to thy Neighbour, are moſt likely to preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and reſolve to embrace them.</p>
               <p>And Laſtly, thou may'ſt conſider thy ſelf with thy Equals either in Eſtate, Age, or other Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109796:10"/> what are thy particular failings, what thy Natural Infirmities, what thoſe things are in thy Words, Actions, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and whole man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Life, which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh thy Reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and make thee leſſ than thy Equals; and what thy aims and ends are, with the Rules of Life thou haſt ſet thy ſelf.</p>
               <p>This is likewiſe a fit time to call to mind what Rules we are to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve in our Apparel; That they be for Health, Honeſty, Comlineſs: that we go rather with the loweſt, than high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109796:11"/> of our Place and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. That the Faſhion be neither Strange, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modeſt, Singular, Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous, nor we the firſt in it. That neither the making nor wearing ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of Pride, Lightneſs, Curioſity, Laſciviouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Prodigality, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs; but ſuch as becomes Holineſs, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and Honeſty; fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the Example of thoſe of our own Rank, that are moſt Sober and Diſcreet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:109796:11"/>
               <head>Directions for Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Devotion:</head>
               <head type="sub">And firſt for Reading.</head>
               <p>HAving thus begun the Day, that thou mayſt walk with God the remainder of it, it will be needful firſt to renew thy peace with God, and then keep it. To this end as ſoon as thou art ready, (if una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable neceſſity hinder not) retire to thy Cloſet, and there in a more ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn manner offer thy morning Sacrifice of Prayer and Thankſgiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, according to the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109796:12"/> Command, <hi>Matth.</hi> 6.6. And that theſe may be the better performed, prepare thy ſelf by Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Meditation; for though theſe be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Exerciſes, yet are they moſt properly joyned together, ſince they mutually help and aſſiſt each other.</p>
               <p>That day is loſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſome time is not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, in ſearching Gods Holy Word, thoſe Divine Monuments: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Books thou mayſt turn over out of choice; this thou muſt read out of Duty, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.29. <hi>They have</hi> Moſes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109796:12"/> 
                  <hi>and the Prophets, let them hear them:</hi> And <hi>John</hi> 5.39. <hi>Search the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures:</hi> And <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> 31.11. <hi>Thou ſhalt read this Law before all Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, that they may hear it, that they may learn, and fear the Lord God, and keep and obſerve all the words of this Law:</hi> So alſo the 6. and the 61. <hi>And theſe words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thy Heart, and thou ſhalt rehearſe them continually to thy Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and ſhalt talk of them when thou tarrieſt in thy Houſe, and as thou walkeſt by the way, and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109796:13"/> when thou lyeſt down, and riſeſt up: Thou ſhalt bind them for a ſign upon thy hand, and they ſhall be as Frontlets between thine Eyes; alſo thou ſhalt write them upon the Poſts of thy Houſe, and upon thy Gates.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt therefore, when you read this Word, lift up your Heart to God for his Leave and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, for the Spirit of Underſtanding and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, that your Mind may be more inlightned, and your Heart more ſtrengthen'd with Grace, by it; for this Word is Spiritual, and contains
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109796:13"/> the hidden things of God in a Myſtery: in which reſpect, 'tis a Sealed Book to thoſe that have not the help of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit. Then you read the Word aright in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, when you have the ſame frame of Heart as the Holy Pen-men had in the Writing of it.</p>
               <p>Read the Word with Hunger and Thirſt after Knowledge, and growth in Grace: and as the means ordained of God for this end.</p>
               <p>Read it with a Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend and Humble, with a tractable and honeſt Heart, trembling at the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109796:14"/> Judgments againſt Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, rejoycing at the Promiſes made to the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, willing, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolving to obey the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. This is the beſt help, and Art of Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: for exceeding Joys, Griefs, Hatred, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do leave the deepeſt impreſſions upon us; we do not ſoon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the Sickneſſes and Pains we have gone through, and the ſhorteſt Wit can remember where he laid his Gold.</p>
               <p>Compare your ways with the Word, bring them to the Rule, ſee how they and that agree,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109796:14"/> be thankful for any Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, humbled and grieved for any Failing, fly to Chriſt to make your Peace, and reſolve to look better to your ways for the time to come.</p>
               <p>Adviſe about, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve upon the means, to bring all into practice; eſpecially thoſe Duties which are laid before thee in thy preſent read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; Obſerve the very expreſſions of Scripture, for they are very uſeful in Prayer, and do often carry a ſecret Emphaſis in them, that will great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly comfort, and affect the Heart that conſiders them.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:109796:15"/>
               <p>In reading ſtill keep <hi>Jeſus</hi> in thine Eye, as the End, Scope, and Subſtance of all the Scripture, in whom they all are <hi>Yea,</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Meditate on, and ſtrive to find out the meaning, and mind of God, in each particular Scripture: and to prevent miſtake and wreſting of Scripture to your hurt, get firſt a clear know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Grounds and Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and indeavour to frame your Life ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the more eaſie, and known Scriptures. Secondly, Be much in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109796:15"/> hearing the Word read in Publick, and Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Learned, and Faithful Miniſter: Let not God's publick Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances be either con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned or neglected, for the ſake of Reading, Prayer, or any other private Duty. This will rather bring a Curſe, than a Bleſſing. And, Laſtly, as above, Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh an humble and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Heart, reſolved to obey when you know God's Will, <hi>Joh.</hi> 7.17. <hi>If any man will do his will, he ſhall know of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine whether it be of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:109796:16"/>
               <p>There is not in the World ſuch another Book, as this Book of God; no Word of like Authority, Holineſs, Wiſdom, true Eloquence, Power, and Eternity; no Book that aims at Gods Glory, and the Salvation of Mans Soul, like this: It diſcovers our miſery by ſin, with the perfect Remedy; it propounds perfect Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to us, and affords the Means to attain it: 'Tis mighty, through God, to prepare for Grace; 'tis the immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Seed to beget us unto Chriſt, the Milk and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:109796:16"/> ſtrong Meat to nouriſh us up in him, and the only Phyſick to recover the Soul from all Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Diſeaſes. By it Chriſt giveth light to the Blind, hearing to the Deaf, ſpeech to the Dumb, ſtrength to the Weak, health to the Sick; yea, by it he doth caſt out Devils, and raiſe Men from the Death of Sin. This is that Book alone, that contains all the rich Legacies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queath'd us by our dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Saviour: 'Tis his laſt Will and Teſtament, Sealed with his own Blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.15. This
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109796:17"/> is the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> or Great Statute Book of the Kingdom of Heaven; containing in it all the mighty Priviledges and Immunities of Gods Children. 'Tis the Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, the Fire, the Sword, the Plow, the Seed, the uſual Inſtrument the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt makes uſe of, to build up, pull down, to plant, purge, and cleanſe; by it we have an Inheritance among them that believe, and are Sanctify'd, and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to God, without ſpot or wrinkle. In ſhort, 'tis the Perfect Rule of Faith and Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109796:17"/> Let any Man but ſeriouſly and impartial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſider the Precepts contained in the word of God, he ſhall aſſuredly find the beſt Direction in the World, for all kind of Moral and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Wiſdom: There are not in all the other Books of Morality toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſo ſound, deep, certain and evident In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions of Wiſdome, (yet moſt ſtrictly joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Innocency and Godlineſs,) as in this one Book.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:109796:18"/>
               <head>Of Prayer.</head>
               <p>PRayer is a Religious repreſenting of our Will, and pouring out our Hearts before God; 'tis the Souls Pulſe, and ſhews the ſtate of the Heart: If Spiritual Life be weak in us, our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers will be ſo too. We do not pray to God, that we may make known our deſires to him, as if he were not acquainted with them, for he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands our Thoughts afar off; neither that we may move him to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and grant our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109796:18"/> for with him there is no Change, or Shadow of turning: but that we may by our Prayers ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that of him, which we believe he is willing to beſtow; Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a neceſſary means, both for God's Glory, and our good, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.14. <hi>This is our Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence which we have to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, that if we ask any thing according to his will, he heareth us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When therefore thou art about to pray, Firſt look into your preſent State, and inquire how all things ſtand between God and you; mark
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109796:19"/> whatſoever occurs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween your ſet times of Prayer, the Providences of God, or Sleights of Satan, what ſins you have committed, what Graces you want, and what Freſh Favours God has beſtowed.</p>
               <p>Tune thy Thoughts and Affections, wind and Screw them up, when thou comeſt to Duty. This is that <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phar</hi> adviſes, <hi>Job</hi> 11.13. <hi>to prepare the Heart, and then to ſtretch forth the Hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>When you are about to addreſs your ſelf to God in Prayer, Fix your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109796:19"/> thoughts upon ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Subject to inlarge upon. There is no queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, if you obſerve your condition well, but you have ſomtimes one er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand to God, ſomtimes another: whether it be to confeſs ſome predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Sin, to beg Pardon of, and Power againſt. You may have in your Eye ſome Grace which you ſtand in more than ordinary need of, and obſerve your own weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and defect in. Run not out into Generals on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for you cannot ſpeak to God of all things at one time; but conſider
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:109796:20"/> the Preſent Caſe of thy Soul, and what buſineſs you have to go to God about at that time: in a particular manner en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large your thoughts on that Subject, and follow it home, till you feel your heart warm'd and affected.</p>
               <p>Implore and expect the Spirit's aſſiſtance, and let thy whole heart be engaged in this work.</p>
               <p>See what thou doſt be according to Gods will, and have a Warrant from his Word: A Command is our Warrant, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is our Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and an Example
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:109796:20"/> our Tract, the Foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of the Flock where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we muſt walk.</p>
               <p>Improve your Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate: This is the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal part of all our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and eſpecially of Prayer, to depend whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon the Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Interceſſion of Chriſt Jeſus, for acceſs to, and acceptance with God.</p>
               <p>Be not ſlight, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal, and curſory, in calling your Sins and Duties, Cods Favours and Promiſes, into a bare and Fruitleſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: if the Heart be not affected with Anger, Fear, Grief,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109796:21"/> and Shame, for Sin; with Joy, and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment of being be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden to God for his Favours, with Hope and Confidence in him, in remembrance of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; if it be not gain'd to a new Reſolution to Reform what is Faulty, and to endeavour after more exactneſs, all your preparation is nothing: Nay, Sin will gather Strength upon you thereby; like idle, Stur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Vagrants, who, when brought before the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, if he either ſay little to them, or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly give them threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109796:21"/> words, but never makes them ſmart for their Offences; they grow thereby ten times more inſolent &amp; lawleſs.</p>
               <p>Keep up Spiritual Frames out of Worſhip; the Fire was to be kept alive upon the Altar, when Sacrifices were not Offer'd, from Morning till Night, from Night till Morning, as well a in the very time of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. One well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, to be ſuch out of Worſhip, as we would be in it: any thing that does unhinge, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſe our Spirits, is inconſiſtent with Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109796:22"/> Services, which are to be perform'd with the greateſt ſedateneſs and gravity. All irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Paſſions diſturb the Serenity of the Spirit: and tho they be allay'd, yet they leave the heart ſome while after, like the Sea, rolling and ſwelling after the Storm is ceaſed. Ill company leaves a Tincture upon us in Worſhip. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im hath mixed himſelf with the People, Hoſea</hi> 7.8. <hi>He is a Cake not tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> This will make our Hearts and Lives half Dough, as well as half Baked. Theſe, and the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:109796:22"/> like, make the Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit withdraw himſelf, and then the Soul lies like a Wind-bound Veſſel, that can make no way: When the Sun departs from us, it carries its Beams along with it; then Darkneſs ſpreads it ſelf over the Earth, and the Beaſts of the Foreſt creep out.</p>
               <p>Be much in Secret E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jaculations to God: Theſe are the pureſt flights of the Soul, that have more of Fervor, and leſs of Carnality. As frequent ſinful Acts ſtrengthen habits of Sin; ſo frequent Religious
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:109796:23"/> acts ſtrengthen habits of Grace.</p>
               <p>Excite and exerciſe particularly a Love to God, and a Dependance on him. The Soul that loves God, when it has to do with him, can mind nothing elſe dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Impreſſion.</p>
               <p>Nouriſh right appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of God in thy mind. Conſider thou art drawing nigh to God, the moſt amiable Object, the beſt of Beings, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of infinite Honour, and the higheſt Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thou canſt give: a God that made the World by a Word, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:109796:23"/> upholds the great frame of Heaven and Earth, a Majeſty above the Conceptions of Angels. View him in his Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Goodneſs, that your Heart may have a true value of the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of ſo great a Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and count it the moſt worthy employment to attend upon him. A Fear of God will make your Worſhip ſerious; a Joy in God, durable; your Affections will be rais'd, when you repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him in the moſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verential, indearing, and obliging Circumſtances. We Honour the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:109796:24"/> of God, when we conſider him with due Reverence, according to the greatneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of his Works: And in this Reverence of his Majeſty, does Worſhip chiefly conſiſt. Preſerve a ſtrong Sence of the Omniſcience, and Omnipreſence of God, who Judges thy inward Affections, and is as really preſent with thee, as if he were Viſible.</p>
               <p>Take heed of inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate deſires after the World: it dulls the Word, and ſtifles all Spiritual breathings af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter God in Duty.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:109796:24"/>
               <p>Be deeply ſenſible of thy preſent wants, and the ſupplies thou mayeſt have in Worſhip. It is pardon thou deſireſt? Apprehend then the blackneſs of Sin, with the aggravations there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as it reſpects God: be deeply ſenſible of the want of Pardon, and the worth of Mercy; indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to get your Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions into ſuch a frame, as condemned Men would be, and as you have ſeen ſome dying Men have. Conſider thou art now at the Throne of Gods Grace, but muſt ſhortly be at
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:109796:25"/> the Bar of his Juſtice: indeavour to ſtir up the ſame affections now, the ſame fixedneſs and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Pleading for Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which thou mayeſt ſuppoſe forlorn Souls will have at Gods Tribunal.</p>
               <p>If thou couldeſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend God as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and offended Judge; or didſt ſee the riches of his Mercy, and his glorious out-goings in the Sanctuary, the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Doles he gives out to thoſe that Spiritually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend upon him: both the one and the other would make thee perform thy Duty humbly, ſincerely,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:109796:25"/> earneſtly, and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately; waiting upon him with thy whole Soul, to have Miſery a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, and Mercy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd. Chriſt does not preſent any Man's Caſe and Duties without a ſenſe of his wants; and ſhall we our ſelves have none of our own?</p>
               <p>Affect thy Heart with what ſupplies thou haſt had in former Worſhip. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> would not have been at leiſure for Idolatry, had they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd the Senſe of the Majeſty of God, diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in his late Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders at <hi>Sinai.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:109796:26"/>
               <p>If any thing intrudes that may choke thy Worſhip, caſt it ſpeedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out: We cannot hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Gnats from buz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing about us, when we are in our Buſineſs; but we may prevent them from ſetling upon us.</p>
               <p>Lay hold on the moſt melting opportunities: when thou findeſt thy Heart in a more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Spiritual Frame, look upon it as a call from God to attend him. Such Impreſſions and Motions are God's voice, inviting us into Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with him, in ſome particular act of Worſhip;
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:109796:26"/> and promiſing Succeſs in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.8. Be not always pouring out Words in Prayer: Pauſe, reflect upon, and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to affect thy Heart, with all thou ſayeſt; in ſilence wait for the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes of the Spiriti.</p>
               <p>Examine thy ſelf at the end of Worſhip, and chide thy ſelf for any Carnality thou percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt; review thy Duty, and examine the reaſon why thou wert ſo low, and Carnal. If any un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy Frames have ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed thee in Worſhip, ſeek them out after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, call them to the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:109796:27"/> Bar, make an exact Scrutiny into the Cauſes of them, and let thine An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and Indignation be raiſed againſt them, that thou mayeſt prevent their incurſion another time: Apply the Blood of Chriſt by Faith for thy Cure; and draw ſtrength from his Death, for the Conqueſt of them. Alſo be humble for them; for God will lift up the humble. Daily exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation is an Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Temptations of the following day; and conſtant examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our ſelves after Duty, is a Preſervative
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:109796:27"/> againſt vain incroach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in following Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>Labour eſpecially af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe two things: To ſee the wants and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections that are in thy beſt Prayers, and abhor them; and in thy greateſt defects, ſee if thou canſt not find ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of Gods Spirit, that ſo thou mayeſt be truly perſuaded in both, That God will through the Merits of Chriſt pardon thy Wants, and accept the Work of his own Spirit. 'Tis a dangerous thing to think that God likes our Prayers well,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:109796:28"/> when we do ſo, ſeeing they have unſeen defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which pollute them: or on the other hand, to be perſwaded that God rejects them when we diſlike them.</p>
               <p>In ſhort, Diligently watch and keep thy ſelf from all Sin, <hi>eſpecially Surfeiting and Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; Luk.</hi> 21.34. and 53. Which make the Heart dull and heavy: Indeavour to grow in all God's Commands, and Faith in all his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes: Keep in thy heart a Catalogue of thy own Sins, Wants and Infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, together with
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:109796:28"/> the ſins and wants of the Land, with the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of God's wrath due thereto: Look at God's Holineſs, and what Holineſs he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in Thee; and then at thy own un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs of thoſe things thou beggeſt of him; thy Neceſſity, and Danger. For ſins that thou art in danger of, becauſe ſtrongly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to them; ask the overcoming of them, uſing all the means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and avoiding the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: ſo for any Grace you want, Importune God after the ſame
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:109796:29"/> manner Never truſt ſo much to thy Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as to neglect any other means ordain'd by God for the obtaining of what thou deſireſt; But uſe them ſtill more conſcionably: neither ever truſt ſo much to other means, as to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Prayer.</p>
               <p>And thus having of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd up thy Prayers to God, and committed thy ſelf, and Cauſe to him, quietly reſt in his good pleaſure; accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Example of <hi>Hannah,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18. and David, 2 <hi>Sam,</hi> 12.20. Doubt not but God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:109796:29"/> hath heard thy Prayer, and in due time will grant what ſhall be moſt for his Glory, and thy Good: This is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the word <hi>Amen.</hi> Look after thy comings in, and gettings by Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; <hi>I will direct my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, and look up.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>How we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive of God in our Devotions.</head>
               <p>HOw to conceive of the Deity in our Prayers and Meditations, is both the deepeſt Point of all Chriſtianity, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:109796:30"/> the moſt neceſſary. So deep, that if we wade into it, we may eaſily drown; but can never find bottom: So neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, that without it, both our Perſons, and ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are Profane, and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious.</p>
               <p>We are all born Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, naturally prone to faſhion God to ſome Form of our awn: whether of a Humane Body, or of an admirable Light; or if our mind have any other more likely and pleaſing Image. There are as many carved Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of God, as there are Minds of men: and as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:109796:30"/> Monſtrous ſhap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s as thoſe corruptious into which they would Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him. Hence all Idolatry ſprang: Men ſet up vain Images of him in ther Fancy, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſet up Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Repreſentations of him in their Temples. The likening of him to Idols of Wood and Stone, and various Metals, was the fruit of an Idea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected in their own minds. Hence alſo all Superſtition receiv'd both its Riſe, and Growth: When we Mint a God according to our own complexion,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:109796:31"/> like to us in mutable and various Paſſions, ſoon angry, ſoon appeas'd, 'tis no wonder we invent ways of pleaſing him, after we have offended him, and think to expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the Sin of out Soul, by ſome Melancholy Devotions, and ſelf-Chaſtiſements. Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition is nothing elſe, but an unſcriptural, and unrevealed dread of God: When men imagin'd him a rigorous and ſevere Maſter, they caſt about for ways to Mitigate him, whom they thought ſo hard to be pleas'd. All the Superſtition this
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:109796:31"/> day living in the World, is built upon this Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation: So natural it is for men to pull down God to their Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, rather than raiſe their Imaginations up to God, Hence ariſes all the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his Mercy, tho' they Repent; meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring God by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted Models of their own Spirit: as tho' his Nature were as difficult to pardon their Offences againſt him, as they are to remit wrongs done to themſelves. And hence alſo all Preſumption, the too common Diſeaſe of the World, ſprings:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:109796:32"/> All the Wickedneſs that is in the World, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but a preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming upon God; ariſing from the ill interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Goodneſs, breaking out upon them, in the Works of Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Providence. God's Patience is appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended to be an appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of their Vices: and from the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Forbearance: they faſhion a God that they believe will ſmile upon their Crimes. <note place="margin">Pſal. 50.20</note> A God they Fancy like themſelves, that would do as they would do: not be angry for what
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:109796:32"/> they count a light Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence. How does the unclean perſon repreſent him to his own thoughts, but as a Goat; the Murderer, as a Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; the ſenſual Perſon, as a Swine: while they Fancy a God indulgent to their Crimes, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Repentance?</p>
               <p>Firſt then, away with all theſe wicked thoughts, theſe groſs Devotions, and without any mental Reſervation, conceive of God Purely, Humbly, Spiritually, as of an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute Being, without Form, without Matter, without Compoſition;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:109796:33"/> yea, as Infinite, without all limit of thought: let our Hearts Adore a Spiritual Majeſty which we cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend, but yet know to be; let us think of him, as one whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is his Juſtice, whoſe Juſtice is his Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, whoſe Power is his Mercy; and whoſe Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Juſtice, Power, Mercy, is himſelf: As Good, without Quality; Great, without Quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Everlaſting, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Time; Preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very where, without Place; containing, all things, without Extent;
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:109796:33"/> and when our thoughts are come to the heighth, let us ſtay there, and be content to wonder in ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence; and ſince we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reach to conceive of him as he is, let us be careful we conceive not of him as he is not.</p>
               <p>But, beſides this awful apprehenſion of the Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, we are to conceive of three Perſons in one Eſſence; not divided, but diſtinguiſh'd. There is nothing wherein the want of Words can grieve us, but in this: here alone, as we can A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore, and not conceive; ſo we can conceive, and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:109796:34"/> not utter. Think here of one Subſtance, in three Subſiſtences; one Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, in three Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; one <hi>Jehovah,</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting, Begotten, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding. Let our thoughts here walk wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, the path is narrow; and the conceit either of three Subſtances, or but one Subſiſtence, is Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable.</p>
               <p>Yet all this will not avail us, if we take not our Mediator with us; if we apprehend not a true Manhood, gloriou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly united to the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, without change of either Nature, without
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:109796:34"/> mixture of both; whoſe Priſence and Merits muſt give paſſage, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance, and Vigour, to our Prayers.</p>
               <p>Thus in Prayer God is to be known and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd of, the diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Perſons, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit; and Ordinarily our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers muſt be directed to the Father, by the Son, through the help of the Holy Ghoſt: <hi>John.</hi> 16.23. <hi>Whatſoever you ask the Father in my name, he will give it you. Epheſ.</hi> 5.20. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.15,27. <hi>We call God Abba Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Spirit which
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:109796:35"/> makes Interceſſion for us.</hi> For ſuch is the Divine diſpenſation of God, the Father, Son, and Holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that tho' they are but one indiviſible Eſſence, and whatſoever any one does out of himſelf, the very ſame do the others alſo; yet they ſuſtain different Perſons and Offices, (as we may ſay), and do the ſame things in different and diſtinct Order: yet ſo as the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of one does not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, but neceſſarily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, the other. In Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, the Father ſuſtains the Perſon and Place of him that is offended by
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:109796:35"/> ſin, that muſt be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peas'd; and does hear, and grant Requeſts: 1 <hi>John.</hi> 2.1. <hi>If we ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father.</hi> The Son ſupplies the Place of a Mediator, and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, by whom Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts aſcend, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come acceptable to the Father: <hi>John.</hi> 16.23: <hi>Revel.</hi> 8.3. <hi>He is the Golden Altar, upon which the Prayers of all Saints are Offer'd, and aſcend as Incenſe. John</hi> 14.6. <hi>No man can come to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but by me.</hi> He is appointed of God, to us; and, being both God and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:109796:36"/> Man, is a fit, and all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficient Mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man: without him no man's Perſon, or beſt Actions, by reaſon of their many Imperfections, can be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
               <p>The Holy Ghoſt does ſupply the Office of a Teacher and Aſſiſtant, to help our Infirmities, and in us to make our Interceſſions and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts for us, that they may be Offer'd to the Father, by the Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Son: <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.26. <hi>We know not what to pray for, as we ought.</hi> If the Spirit do not work
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:109796:36"/> together with our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, there would be no goodneſs at all in them: no, not ſo much as Truth and Uprightneſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Chriſt will not offer them to his Father for us; therefore Prayers muſt be made in the Spirit, and through his help.</p>
               <p>And thus Chriſt, by the Office of his Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation and Interceſſion, is an Advocate to his Church, and does in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven apply his Merits, and further the cauſe of our Salvation, with his Father. And the Spirit alſo is an Advocate, by
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:109796:37"/> Energy and Operation, by Inſtruction and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, by his Counſel and Inſpiration inabling us to manage our own buſineſs, and plead our own Cauſe: he does not indeed interceed, nor ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear before God in Perſon for us, as Chriſt does; but makes Interceſſion in, and by our ſelves, giving us acceſs unto the Father, imboldening us in our Fears, helping us in our Infirmities, and bringing thoſe things which were blotted out, and forgot, into our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance: <note place="margin">Ephſ. 2.18. Hebr. 10.15.19.</note> Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and Directing us <note place="margin">John 14.26.</note>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:109796:37"/> how to order and ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite our own buſineſs, what Evidences to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, what Witneſſes to prepare, what Offices to attend, what preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to make, againſt the time of hearing. And laſtly, he makes up Failings by his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and gathers Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments to further our Suit, which we our ſelves obſerv'd not. So when we know not what to Pray, nor what to do, when in our own ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions the whole buſineſs of our Peace and comfort lyes a blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding; the Spirit does
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:109796:38"/> then help our Infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, preſenting Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by ſecret intima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, by deeep and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expreſſible groans, unto him who is the Searcher of hearts, and who knows the mind of the Spirit, which we our ſelves cannot expreſs. Thus as an Infant cries and complains, for want of ſleep, and yet knows not that it is ſleep which he wants; as a ſick man goes to a Phyſician, and complains that ſome Phyſick he wants, but knows not the thing he asks for: So the ſoul of a Chriſtian, by the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:109796:38"/> aſſiſtance of the Spirit, is incourag'd to requeſt things of God, which yet of themſelves do paſs the knowledge and underſtanding of thoſe that ask them. <note place="margin">Rom. 8.26. Epheſ. 3.19. Phil. 4.7. 1 Cor. 14.13.</note> Hence the Holy Ghoſt call'd another Comforter, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſupplies the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral abſence of Chriſt, <note place="margin">Joh. 14.16.</note> brings him down to a Chriſtian, Forms him in his heart, evidences him, and the Virtue of his Paſſion and Reſurrection, in the powerful diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of his Holy Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: therefore when our Saviour ſpeaks of ſending the Holy Spirit,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:109796:39"/> he adds; <hi>I will not leave you Comfortleſs, I will come to you: when the World ſees me not, you ſee me. John</hi> 14.18,20.</p>
               <p>Now becauſe of this Order of the Deity, the Father being firſt, and becauſe of the different Places they ſuſtain in the work of our ſalvation; the Counſel and Will of all three is, That the Father ſhould be Pray'd unto, and Worſhipp'd in the only Mediation of the Son, through the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spirit: and therefore the Father is fitly nam'd alone; becauſe the Son, by Voluntary diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:109796:39"/> has the Part of a Mediator, and the Holy Spirit the Office of an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructor, teaching us what to Pray.</p>
               <p>In Wiſhing the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of things, it is not neceſſary to name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Perſons; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Oh that thou would'ſt bleſs me indeed, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large my Coaſt.</hi> Somtimes 'tis lawful to name in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely; <hi>Acts</hi> 4.24. <hi>Lord, thou art God, who haſt made Heaven and Earth.</hi> It is lawful alſo, <note place="margin">Act. 22.24</note> when we name Perſons, to name only one, or two: provided we name not one, as excluding
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:109796:40"/> the other two; nor two, as excluding the third. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.14. <hi>The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the love of God, and the Communion of the Holy Ghoſt be with you all.</hi> The Apoſtles begin their Epiſtles thus: <hi>Grace and peace from God the Father, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt. Acts</hi> 7.59. <hi>Stephen</hi> pray'd, <hi>Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit.</hi> If we exclude the other, while we fix our heart upon one; our Prayer is Sin: if we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain all, and mention but one, we offend not. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly we may name the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:109796:40"/> Spirit before the Son, and the Son before the Father, <note place="margin">Revel. 1.4.5.</note> and <hi>Saint Paul</hi> more than once names the Son before the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; <hi>Now our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, and God, even the Father, comfort your hearts.</hi> 2. Cor. 13.14. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.16.</p>
               <p>Here we may add the Rules we are to obſerve in calling upon God. As firſt, that we call upon him, by thoſe Titles by which he has been pleas'd to make himſelf known unto us in his holy Word. That we conſider of him in Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as an All-ſufficient
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:109796:41"/> God, and ſee in him the things we deſire. <note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.17.</note> The Saints ſtill ſet God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, as having that in him for which they pray. <note place="margin">Acts. 4.24.</note> We muſt call upon God by ſuch Names, Titles, and Deſcriptions, <note place="margin">Pſal. 86.15,16.</note> as are moſt apt to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flame Deſire, ſtir up Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, confirm Faith, or incourage the Heart; according as our neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and diſpoſition do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. If many and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral requeſts be to be put up; then ſuch Titles and Names muſt be uſed, as may perſwade us we ſhall be heard in all. If particular requeſts be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:109796:41"/> then choice is to be made of ſuch Titles and Names, as may help the heart in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular. <note place="margin">Gen. 24.12 Acts. 1.24. Pſ. 94.1. 2 Ch. 20 6 Dan. 9.4. Iſa. 64.8.</note> It is neceſſary for one that would make a good entrance into Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, to acquaint himſelf with the true underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the manifold Names and Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, recorded in Scripture; and then to make choice of ſuch to name him by, as are ſpecially to be exercis'd in granting his requeſt, and moſt fit to incite Reverence, and confirm Faith. Laſtly the expreſs Command of God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:109796:42"/> to Worſhip him by any Image, or Simili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude. <note place="margin">Deut. 4.16,17. Exod. 10.4.</note> And he himſelf, in many places of Scripture, ſhews how ſeverely he will puniſh them that give his Glory to dumb Idols.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Family Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</head>
               <p>I If thou art Maſter of a Family, be watchful over thy Charge, with all diligence and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs.</p>
               <p>Inſtruct thy Children, and Servants, in the knowledge of God.</p>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:109796:42"/>
               <p>Pray with them, and for them:</p>
               <p>Bring them to Gods Ordinances.</p>
               <p>Prevent, and remove, all occaſions of their hearing, ſeeing, or doing Evil.</p>
               <p>But above all, be ſure to go before them in a good Example. If a Maſter be a Swearer, Drunkard, or the like, 'tis madneſs for himever to expect a Sober Family: his Houſe ſhall be a Den of Swearers, Drunkards and Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Auguſtus</hi> his Court is fill'd with Scholars; <hi>Tiberius's</hi> with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:109796:43"/> and <hi>Julian's</hi> with Apoſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Duties relating to our Calling.</head>
               <p>YOur Cloſet-Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-duties, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, we are in the next place to ſet about the work of our Calling: The Law impos'd upon <hi>Adam</hi> binds all his Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity; <hi>In the ſweat of thy Face thou ſhalt eat Bread, till thou return unto the Ground.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt then, adventure
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:109796:43"/> not on any courſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out good aſſurance that it be in it ſelf Lawful; <hi>Acts.</hi> 9.25. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.20.</p>
               <p>Make not a Calling of that, which was never made to be one. There are many things Lawful to do, which are not Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Live by: Lawful as Delights, and Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; which are not Lawful as Callings.</p>
               <p>Reſolve not upon that for thy Calling, which is rather hurtful, than profitable to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
               <p>Chuſe that Calling which is fitteſt for thee: when thy Inclination,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:109796:44"/> Education, and Gifts, concur in one and the ſame Calling; that is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo.</p>
               <p>If thou art altogether averſe to that Calling, for which thou haſt been bred up, and deſign'd; chooſe then the neareſt of kin to it that thou canſt like, that ſo thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation and time may not be loſt: Thus one bred: up for the Miniſtry, may make choice of ſome other Profeſſion that hath to do with Learning; as Law, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, or the like.</p>
               <p>Ever begin, and end all thy Works with Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:109796:44"/> begging God's bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing on thy Labours, and commending all thy indeavours to him that muſt either wither, or proſper them: Likewiſe upon any unexpected ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident, or when thou doubteſt what to do, go to God for direction; make known, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit thy Caſe to him: he hath not only wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom for thy Salvation, but for thy outward di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. too.</p>
               <p>Carefully avoid all Covetouſneſs; whereby men deſign no farther end, than the meer ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of Wealth and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:109796:45"/> Riches. This is the root of all evil. Would'ſt thou remedy it? Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain thy Affections from the World; keep thy deſires within Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs; and, as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture terms it, <hi>without <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>ouſneſs, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with what thou haſt, Heb.</hi> 13.5. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee a particular Providence of God in all things that come to paſs, and befall thee: Health or Sickneſs, Riches or Poverty, Liberty or Bondage. He raiſeth up, and pulleth down; he only giveth Power to get Wealth, and taketh
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:109796:45"/> it away again at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: He Ruleth the Kingdoms of the Earth, and giveth them to whom he pleaſeth. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thy Conſcience that God is thy Father and Portion, and that all things befall thee by his holy Will, and Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Providence and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment: Seek no more than the things which are neceſſary and ſufficient, even Food convenient. And laſtly, raiſe your. Affections from the World, to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter things.</p>
               <p>As carefully ſhun all Injuſtice; whereby men
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:109796:46"/> abuſe their Calling, to the hurt and hindrance of others. <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.8. For prevention, conſider this Sin is againſt the expreſs Word of God; 1 <hi>Theſſal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Let no man oppreſs, or defraud his Brother in any mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; For the Lord is the avenger of all ſuch things:</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 2.11.</note> That it makes all our Worſhip and Service a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bomination; <hi>Eſay.</hi> 1.13. to the 17. That the Curſe of God it the practice of it; <hi>Deut.</hi> 25.16. <hi>Thou ſhalt not have in thy Bag two man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Weights, a great and a ſmall; nor in thy
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:109796:46"/> Houſe divers Meaſures: But thou ſhalt have a right and a juſt Weight, a perfect and juſt Meaſure ſhalt thou have; For all that do ſuch things, and all that do unrighteouſly, are an abomination to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beware of Ambition; whereby men think better of themſelves, than there is juſt cauſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come malecontent with their Condition, and ſeek for themſelves grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and better Things and Places. Examples of this we have in <hi>Adam,</hi> and <hi>Abſalom, &amp;c.</hi> One of the beſt Remedies in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:109796:47"/> World for this Diſeaſe of the Mind, is the ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conſideration of our ſelves, what we are, in reſpect of our Bodies, but Duſt; in reſpect of our diſpoſitions, altogether ſet on Sin; and in our Places and Callings, at beſt but weak and worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Inſtruments in the hand of God: the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of ten Thouſand.</p>
               <p>Be not evercome with Envy; let not thy heart pine away to ſee others placed in a better condition, than thy ſelf: Conſider, that all can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not have Rich, Eaſy, and Honourable Employs;
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:109796:47"/> the neceſſity of the whole requires that ſome ſhould drudge in baſer and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Offices: the higheſt Callings were not or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Pride, or pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate benefit of Man; but for the common good. There ſhould be no ſhame of that, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there can be no want: were there none to grind at the Mill, there would ſoon be none to ſit on the Throne. Grudge not thy own Lot; for not the meaneſt calling, but is a Service unto Chriſt, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 3.24. and has a promiſe of a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:109796:48"/> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 12.22. Neither envy thou ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's; for not the greateſt, but is attended with Worldly Vexati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Remember, Envy is a denyal of Gods Providence: To be ſad at the Temporal Goods or Gifts of another, as counting him unworthy of them, is a reflection on the Author of thoſe Gifts, and an accuſing Providence of an unjuſt, or unwiſe diſtribution. This temper is peculiar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the product of ſelf-love, which affects the Principality of the World, and the Conduct of God
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:109796:48"/> in diſtributing his Goods; that he muſt not give, but to whom we pleaſe. It ſeems to be a compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of our fiſt Parents pride; they envyed God a Felicity by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, they would be like him, they would be as Gods: This temper we are all too ſubject to, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 37.1.</p>
               <p>Shun <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Impatience; which is a diſquietneſs of mind, ariſing from the continual troubles that are incident unto all conditions, making men Weary of their Place, and condition of Life. Conſider, for
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:109796:49"/> Remedy, that the Impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a contempt of God's Government: La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor is the condition of our being; we had not been, but that we might be ſtill buſy: There is no Art, but has its La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor; which va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> in meaſure, according to the will of the doer: difficulty is not ſo much in the Work, as in the Agent; that which you complain of, has been undertaken by others, not with facility only, but pleaſure: and what you chooſe for eaſe, has been abhorred by others, as tedious. Never think
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:109796:49"/> to detract from your Buſineſs, but add to your Will; beſides, Hours never go away ſo mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily, as in the Fellowſhip of Work: There is a tediouſneſs in doing no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. But above all, take heed of fretting at God's management of thy own particular con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns: this may lead thee to a curſing God; and is indeed an initial ſecret ſwelling againſt him, and flying in his Face, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.12,21. <hi>He ſhall curſe his King and his Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Guard thy ſelf eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt thoſe ſins
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:109796:50"/> which by reaſon of thy Vocation, courſe of Life, and converſation, thou haſt the greateſt, and ſtrongeſt inticements un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: thus the Courtier's ſin is to make a God of his Prince, 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.18. The Souldier's ſin, to abuſe his weapon to private Revenge, <hi>Luke.</hi> 3.14. The Lawyer's ſin, to betray, or delay his Clients Cauſe; The Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es ſin, to pervert Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or refuſe to do Juſtice, through Fear, or Favour, or Reward: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Calling, as it hath its Myſtery, ſo its ſpecial ſins, and Snares, which
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:109796:50"/> the Devil and Cuſtom, for gain, or Credit among wicked men, hath made to ſeem not only law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but neceſſary; ſuch as a man can hardly ſhun, without expoſing himſelf to cenſure. Look therefore narrowly to the light of Scripture, to find out theſe ſins; and then as carefully avoid them.</p>
               <p>Be diligent in thy Calling: <hi>The Sluggard de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireth, and hath nothing; but the diligent hand maketh rich.</hi> Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on comes by leiſure; no excellent thing is done at once. Do not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:109796:51"/> all thou canſt at one time, but take new dayes: where the heart is unwilling, prorogati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hinders; but where there is no want of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, delay ſharpens the ſtomach; and that which we do unwillingly leave, we long to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take.</p>
               <p>Be ſober: Fly not out, and ſtart beyond thy proper calling, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6. While you keep your ſelf in your Place, you are under God's ſpecial Protection, as the Bird in the Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 22.6. But whenſoever thou run'ſt out of God's
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:109796:51"/> Protection, thou may'ſt juſtly fear his deſertion: and if Satan once find thee idle, he will labour to employ thee in ſome of his works.</p>
               <p>Be Chearful; Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly thinking on the Condition of thy Being: The Bird was made to Fly, and Man to Labour. Be Provident; let not thy opportunites ſlip, neither be thou circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented, and enſnared by Fraud, Falſhood and Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſhip.</p>
               <p>Uſe Truth, Plainneſs, and Equity: Love thy Neighbour as thy ſelf, obſerving that Royal
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:109796:52"/> Law, the Standard of all Juſtice, <hi>To do unto others, as thou would'ſt others ſhould do unto thee. Matth.</hi> 7.12.</p>
               <p>Above all labour e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to retain in thy heart a habit of Religion that may keep you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways as in the preſence of God.</p>
               <p>Prefer thoſe Actions of thy life that moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thee, be ſure to mind them moſt, to do them firſt; let other things of leſs moment give place to theſe. Let every buſineſs have its due time; and then think of it ſufficiently and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:109796:52"/> to purpoſe, remitting and checking all other thoughts and cares at that time as unſeaſonable and interruptions.</p>
               <p>In all thy deſignes of temporal advantages, keep thy Expectations and Hope low, clog them with ſuſpicions, abate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and allays; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe thy expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will not only cheat thee, but render the good thou ſhalt attain inſipid, becauſe leſs than what thou didſt expect.</p>
               <p>The idle man, that for want of a courſe to live in, impoveriſheth himſelf and Family, ſuch
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:109796:53"/> a man is a burden to his Friends, and to the Commonwealth, an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore to his Kindred, the ſhame of his Name, and ruin of his Houſe: he bequeatheth miſery to his Off-ſpring, inſtead of plenty; and inſtead of giving his Children God's bleſſing, and his, he pulls upon himſelf God's Curſe, and theirs. I <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. <hi>He is worſe than an Infidel.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Civil Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</head>
               <p>Civil Converſation is an honeſt, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:109796:53"/> and Virtuous kind of living in this World: a thing, not only profitable, but neceſſary, for the perfection of Human life; A moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Cure to thoſe two great diſtempers, that grow upon the Mind, through Solitude: A baſe Abjection, and vain Preſumption of ſpirit. By reaſon whereof, men become either diſtruſtful of their own Actions, and fearful of other mens Judgment: or elſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported wih too good and great an Opinion of themſelves, and too low and ſmall an account and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:109796:54"/> eſteem of others. Inſtead of theſe, it gives a man a certain graceful confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and aſſurance, without Impudence or Affectation, in all his Actions: It teaches him to be civil, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſing himſelf; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſant, without Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering others.</p>
               <p>ſome men indeed there are, to whom Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is a moſt burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, and uneaſy thing: 'Tis an intollerable trouble, they ſay, and kind of Subjection to them, to frame fitting anſwers to all manner of Talk, and obſerve
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:109796:54"/> ſuch circumſtances, as the Quality of Perſons, and their own Honor do require. For one man that's tolerable in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, they tell us they meet with more than hundreds, that either through Pride or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, through Folly or Ambition, through ſome unſeemly behavior or other, are ſo troubleſom and vexatious, that they find themſelves rather Tired than Refreſhed by company. But doubtleſs theſe men are under a miſtake; for what tho' the number of Knaves and Fools, of Lew'd and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:109796:55"/> Vain men, be greater than the accompliſh'd and Virtuous, yet ought we therefore to baniſh our ſelves the Society of Mankind; and not rather to conſort our ſelves with men of Worth and Virtue, with ſuch as are Pious and good, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by our minds may be confirm'd and fortifi'd? For it is a moſt certain truth, that the judgment, we make of our ſelves, is not our own, but we borrow it from others: and being by divers perſons, either by Signs or otherwiſe reproved for the ſame fault, at
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:109796:55"/> length we are content to ſubmit our ſelves to the common Opinion of all men, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge our Imperfections, and to frame our ſelves to do, to leave, to change, to correct, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of other Men.</p>
               <p>Our converſation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men is twofold; according to which our behavior muſt be regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated. The one is Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Common, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, ſuch as our Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs do daily lead us into; we change from thoſe we know, to thoſe we do not, without our
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:109796:56"/> choice, or conſent: The other is Special, Affected, and Deſired company. In both, our chief care conſiſts in theſe two things: In the right Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment of our Tongue, and of our Behaviour.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, let thy revenues be far greater than thy expence. Wiſe Nature has given us two Ears, and but one Tongue, that we may hear much, and ſpeak little. And commonly the weakeſt in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding delight to hear themſelves ſpeak; which gave occaſion to the Proverbs, that it is one
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:109796:56"/> piece of Wiſdom for a man to hide his Folly; That He knoweth not how to ſpeak, that knows not how to be ſilent: For as words well utter'd ſhew Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence and Learning; ſo ſilence, well kept, ſhews Prudence and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity. <hi>A Fools voice is known by the Multitude of his words; but he that refraineth his lips is wiſe. Prov.</hi> 10.19. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.3. and 10.14. Words well conſider'd, like Money well employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, tend to the profit and advantage both of him that receiveth, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:109796:57"/> him that disburſeth: And as it is not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Coyn, or Pay out falſe Money; ſo is it as unlawful to invent, or ſpeak, what may turn to the Prejudice or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of others. There are three ſpecial ſeaſons, wherein a man ought to ſpeak: And in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther caſes, ſilence is to be prefer'd. Firſt, when things come in queſtion we underſtand perfectly well. Again, when ſuch matters ariſe we are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to ſpeak to. And in the laſt place, when men have a good opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of us, and in things
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:109796:57"/> they will willingly hear, and eaſily give credit to us.</p>
               <p>Heedfully obſerve thoſe things that beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy and adorn our ſpeech. The honourable part of Talk is to give occaſion, and then to moderate, and paſs to ſomething elſe, to vary in our Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and intermingle ſpeech of the preſent oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion with Arguments; Tales, with Reaſons; as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Queſtions, with telling of Opinions: 'tis a dull thing to Tire and Jade any thing too far, to be too much in any thing: ſo as to give
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:109796:58"/> another occaſion of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſs. This makes a man cheap, to ſpeak perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to the thing in hand, and agreeably to the Perſon, is better than Eloquence.</p>
               <p>A man muſt avoid all thoſe things, which make his Diſcourſe leſs delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to the hearers: He muſt not be ſo brief, as to be obſcure; nor tire men with ſuperfluous words, and tedious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faces, impertinent Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances and Digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Diſcourſe is the Image of the Thought, which it ought to ſet forth ſo clearly, that it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:109796:58"/> may be ſeen, and as it were touch'd with the Finger. We ſhall find upon reflection, that the delight and pleaſure, we feel and conceive in a Diſcourſe, proceeds ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Images form'd by Words in our Minds; or the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance between the Words and the Things, whoſe Image they bear: So that 'tis either the truth that pleaſeth us, or the conformity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt Words and things. Yet in ſpeech we may obſerve ſome perſons have ſo ſtrange a force and ſweetneſs in the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:109796:59"/> delivery of their Words; that, altho they be nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proper nor well pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, yet do ſo delight our Ears and Minds with their Harmony, that we neither ſearch nor deſire any thing farther: while other men, whoſe Words are more pure and correct, loſe their force for want of a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Voice in delivering. A man ought therefore to be very exact in mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring the force of his Voice, that he offend not other mens Ears by raw and harſh ſounds: And alſo careful to fill his Memory with proper
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:109796:59"/> Terms; So contriving it, that the Images of things, and their Names be of ſo ſtrict a Cohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, that the Images and Expreſſions may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent themſelves together. One reſembles the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to a Printing preſs: A Printer who has no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Gothick</hi> Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters, let the Treatiſe be never ſo good, can Print it in no other. The ſame may be ſaid of thoſe, whoſe Memories are full of nothing but impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Terms. A man's Words ought to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Significant, and of efficacy: A Gentleman
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:109796:60"/> ought not to make pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with Farthings and Liards, uſing ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions as are baſe and low, and defil'd by the uſe of the Vulgar People; who, by turning words from their Original mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, to ſignifie vile and ſordid things, have forc'd upon them many and different Images, hereby debaſing and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luting them.</p>
               <p>It is certain, that a Sentence receives its Force and Vigor from the Reputation and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſpeaker; the Words and Expreſſions
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:109796:60"/> by which it is utter'd and the Action, and Air of the Countenance, theſe have their peculiar Charm, which ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly influence the minds of men. A graceful Majeſty of geſture, and goverment of Face and Countenance, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Speech or Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, is of great force and effect, for it gains a kind of Reputation, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem, and Reverence, and where that is, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt every thing becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. There is as well Eloquence of Body, as of Mind; and a man may Cancel the force
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:109796:61"/> of his Words by his Countenance.</p>
               <p>But to give a more exact and ſure Rule ſor the Tongue; If thou would'ſt rightly Govern it, begin with the Heart. The diſorders of the Tongue uſually proceed from the Diſtempers of the Heart; Idle words, from vanity of thoughts; raſhneſs of ſpeech, from haſtineſs of Spirit; boaſting, from pride of heart: <hi>Out of the abundance of the Heart, the Mouth ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="111" facs="tcp:109796:61"/>
               <p>Beg of God, that he would be with thy Mouth, as he was with <hi>Moſes,</hi> touch thy Tongue, as he did <hi>Jeremy,</hi> teach thee at all times, what to ſay, and put words into thy Mouth; give thee the Tongue of the Learned, as he did <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah;</hi> and a door of utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as he did <hi>Paul;</hi> that he would circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and pare off the fore skin of thy Lips, all Superfluous, Fooliſh, and vain Words, that ſo thy Language may be pure, and thy Voice ſweet; that no ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, idle, nor raſh words
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:109796:62"/> break forth; that he would delight to uſe thy Tongue, as an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of much ſervice and praiſe to his Name, and good to others, making thy Words proſper and prevail to all good intents and Purpoſes. <note place="margin">Exod. 4.12. Iſa. 50,4. Jere. 1.6. 1 Chr. 1.5. Act. 13.9.</note> As God is Lord over our Tongue, ſo is he Author of all its gifts.</p>
               <p>Mark, and moan for the errors as well of thy Tongue, as Wayes. <note place="margin">Joh. 40.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Once have I ſpoken, but I will not anſwer; yea twice, but I will proceed no farther.</hi> Keep a good correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:109796:62"/> as between Heart and Tongue, to ſpeak what thou thinkeſt; So between Tongue and Hand, to do what thou ſayeſt: Pay thy Vows to God, and perform thy promiſes to Men; and ſay no more to either, than what thou can'ſt and wilt do.</p>
               <p>Conform thy Mind and Affections to thy Words; indeavour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to be, what thou deſireſt to ſeem: A man cheats not the World ſo much as Himſelf, when he ſtrives to ſeem grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wiſer, or better than
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:109796:63"/> he really is, and covets to be eſteemed a Wiſe, Juſt, and Pious man; but neither cares or endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to make himſelf poſſeſſour of theſe Virtues. 'Tis impoſſible this man's deſigns ſhould take effect.</p>
               <p>Labour for Patience, and moderation: Be ſlow to Speak, and ſlow to Wrath, truſt not thy ſelf, without the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt watchfulneſs, to ſpeak of thoſe Perſons, who have wrong'd, or injur'd thee; leſt Envy, Malice, or any other bitter Ingredient inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly mingle themſelves with thy Words. Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:109796:63"/> arm thy ſelf a gainſt all Paſſion of Joy, Anger, and the like; but be ſure thou never ſpeakeſt when thou art in any: Not only the Wicked, as <hi>Rabſhakeh, Nabal,</hi> and <hi>Herod,</hi> but even the moſt Holy, when tranſported with diſorder'd Paſſions, have broke forth into unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed ſpeeches: <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> overcome with Anger, <hi>Job</hi> with grief, and <hi>Peter</hi> wth Joy, could not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their unruly Tongues. Nothing more expoſes a man, more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays and ſurpriſes the
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:109796:64"/> Powers of Reaſon, than Paſſion; which is bred and nouriſh'd, by Pride, Folly, and Self-love.</p>
               <p>Be not too poſitive in affirming any thing, leſt thou prove miſtaken: and if thou haſt erred, perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere not in it, think it no ſhame to ſubmit to truth, but rather rejoyce that thou haſt found it.</p>
               <p>Be not too fond of your own Opinion, nor concern'd, if others differ from you, and do not ſo much regard what you ſay, as you imagin they ought: make not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe your end; let neither it, nor diſtaſt,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:109796:64"/> have too great an Influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon you in any thing, or Power either to exalt, deject, or raiſe any unruly Paſſion in thee.</p>
               <p>Conſider alwaies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou ſpeakeſt, what thou art about to ſay, and to whom; Be not over haſty, and inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate, either in thy Speeches or Actions; Pauſe and Deliberation do many times diſcover many Ingredients of Wiſdom and Prudence, requiſite to the choice of Words and Actions, and the manner of doing them: Never run into any concluſion, how
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:109796:65"/> quick ſo ever thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt be in any matter of importance, ſuddenly. How many Witty men have fallen into great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, becauſe they would not give themſelves time to think, nor their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations time to cool, whereas calm and flow men, who paſs for dull in the common eſtimation, as they ſearch after truth with more deliberation, ſo they find it out with more certainty.</p>
               <p>In all diſputes, and pleading of Caſes, or the like, <note place="margin">Prov. 15.28.</note> uſe but few words, and thoſe as ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificant and expreſſive,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:109796:65"/> as the matter will bear, and home to the point, and as much as poſſible, ſhorten the excurſions of other men about circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of no moment, keeping them ſtill to the main Hinge of the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>It doth greatly add to a man's Reputation to have good Forms. The Exerciſes in Univerſities and Schools, are of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory and Invention, either to ſpeak by heart, that which we have ſet down Verbatim; or elſe to ſpeak Extempore: Whereas in Action there is little uſe of either of
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:109796:66"/> theſe; but moſt things we utter are neither Verbally premeditated, nor meerly Extemporal; therefore Exerciſe ſhould be ſo fram'd, to take a little breathing to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Heads, and then to ſet and form the Speech <hi>Extempore.</hi> This may be done either with uſing Notes, (for in moſt Actions they are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd) or elſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out them.</p>
               <p>Speak not the evil thou knoweſt of any man; blame the Action, not the Perſon, unleſs lawfully called by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or to thoſe
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:109796:66"/> whom it concerneth thee to Reform and Reclaim, or when the conceal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may make thee guilty, or acceſſory, or to prevent certain dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage to thy Soul, Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or Eſtate of thy Neighbour; or laſtly, when ſome particular, remarkable Judgment is upon a notorious Sinner, that God may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd in his juſt Judgments, and Sinners wain'd from ſuch practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>Impart to no man the evils thou haſt heard ſpoken of him, neither bring any thing to light,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:109796:67"/> upon which Scandals may enſue.</p>
               <p>Seek to ſtop evil Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe, by a timely and wiſe turning of it to the lawful affairs of this life; for where Religion will not be admitted, theſe things may take place.</p>
               <p>Let not others ſee that thou know'ſt their defects, ill actions, or hard thoughts they have of thee, or ſuch as thou loveſt, or any offence committed againſt thee; neither the good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they bear to thy Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
               <p>Make good uſe to thy ſelf of all things that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:109796:67"/> fall out in Converſation: mark every paſſage and circumſtance, and lay up, and appropriate whatſoever is commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable; and indeavour to imitate wiſe men, not only in their words and manner of delivery, but even in their common behaviour, ſo far as it will become your Place and Perſon. All the profit we reap by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, flows from the diligent obſervation, and imitation of others.</p>
               <p>Envy no man his due and juſt praiſe, as if it abated thy eſteem: ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoyce, to hear a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:109796:68"/> man well repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of. Not only ſtop thine Ears, but ſet thy Speech and Countenance againſt whiſpering De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractions from thy Neighbour's good name. And if thou canſt not without danger by word reprove men, let thy Countenance, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and contrary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, teſtifie thy diſlike. Let the Good thou ſeeſt be matter of content, thankfulneſs to God, and thy own imitation: And the Evil, of Grief, Humiliation, and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:109796:68"/>
               <p>When men report good of thee; if it be true, repreſs ſuch diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe as wiſely and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly as thou canſt: And if not, indeavour to make it ſo. When men report evil of thee; be not ſo inquiſitive who rais'd it, as to make good uſe of it to thy ſelf: this evil does not ariſe without Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence. <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16.11.</note> And tho' the report be falſe, in reſpect of ſuch or ſuch a Fact; yet conſider whether thou haſt not run into the appearance and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions of thoſe evils; and let this humble
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:109796:69"/> thee, and make thee more circumſpect. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſee Gods wiſe and good Providence; not only in diſcovering the Folly and Malice of wicked men, who raiſe and take up an evil Report againſt thee with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out cauſe; but in giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee warning to look to thy ſelf, leſt thou deſerveſt thus to be ſpoken of. Great is the advantage thou may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt receive, by the wiſe improvement of the Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings and Revilings of an Enemy; for tho' he be a bad Judge, he is a good Remembrancer:
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:109796:69"/> and you may hear from him thoſe things, which Friends and Flatterers will never admoniſh you of.</p>
               <p>Wrong no man, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Life, Name, Chaſtity, or Eſtate: do all the good thou canſt, according to thy ability and opportunities, even to thy very Enemies, and forgive all the wrongs men do unto thee.</p>
               <p>Let your Actions be always ſuitable to your Perſon, Place, and Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; and then you need never be aſhamed whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be your Judge.</p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:109796:70"/>
               <p>So frame your ſelf to the Time, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, as neither to ſerve them, nor ſullenly neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them; yielding ſo far, as may neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray Goodneſs, nor coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance Evil; Meaſure in a juſt Ballance, and maintain both thine own Honour, and the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of others. Learn rightly to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween men, and not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly reſpect all alike: be not in bondage to their Faces, or Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; neither diſmantle or expoſe thy ſelf to their ſcorn or injury, by too much goodneſs or
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:109796:70"/> facility of Nature: this ſets the faireſt Gloſs upon a man. It is a point of great wiſdom to keep our affections undiſcover'd in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny: If thou concealeſt thy own Judgment, thou ſhalt the better diſcover another man's Opinion.</p>
               <p>Apply your ſelf ſo to your Superiors, as to convince them of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and eſteem you bear them, and demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate that you do it not out of Facility, but Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard; for nothing inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the affections of great men more, than a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and graceful addreſs.</p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:109796:71"/>
               <p>Do nothing that may diſtaſte another man's ſenſe or imagination.</p>
               <p>As in Apparel ſo in Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, a man ſhould know not only what is good, but what becomes him. Our behaviour (which is as it were the Garment of the mind) ought to have the conditions of a Garment: It ought to be ſuch as is in Faſhion; not too curious, and coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but ſuitable to our Quality; and ſo ſhap'd, as to ſet forth any good faculty of the Mind, and to ſupply and hide any deformity. Neither ſhould it be ſo ſtrait,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:109796:71"/> as to ſtrain the mind, or hinder and repreſs the motion thereof in Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>In all thy Aſſociati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons let this be a general Direction, thorowly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Deſigns and Ends upon which they were contracted; care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inquire into thy own condition, and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and impartially judge how much thou do'ſt contribute to the upholding that Amity: and as thou findeſt thy ſelf of Importance, and ſubſervient to the ends they have in deſigning thy Friendſhip, ſo far
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:109796:72"/> value thy ſelf, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to be valued; and never imagin, that any man will quit his own particular advantage and profit, to ſerve thee; or procure thine, on a friendſhip eſtabliſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mutual convenience.</p>
               <p>When thou canſt not ſhun evil Company, in reſpect of the common affairs of Life, be ſure thou giveſt no advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to them, either to ſpeak ill of thee, or of Religion: <note place="margin">1 Tim. 5.14.</note> let thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation be honeſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blamable, and harmleſs; as ſoon as poſſible leave them; and while thou
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:109796:72"/> art with them be full of Fear, leſt thou fall. Raiſe thy heart to a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of their Sin, yet compaſſionating the Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: and when ever thou ſeeſt or heareſt any Wickedneſs, let it be a grief and vexation of Spirit to thee; Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately lift up thy heart to God, and before him confeſs it; diſdain all li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of it, and pray to be kept from it. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe beg of God to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give thy Companion his ſin, and that he would grant him the grace to repent.</p>
               <p>There is a ſtrange at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractive
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:109796:73"/> and imperious power in all Company, to impoyſon and pervert even the beſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions: By holding fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliar correſpondence with lewd men, there ſteals upon a man a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, and inſenſible diſlike of his former ſober cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; he begins to cenſure and renounce his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ways of Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, as too ſtrict and reſtraining, and full of unneceſſary abridgment. The love he bears mens Perſons, leſſens daily the diſlike of their ſins: At firſt they appear leſs hainous, then they
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:109796:73"/> ſeem ſmall and Venial; afterwards he thinks them tolerable and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, till at laſt he comes to juſtifie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend, to approve and practiſe them.</p>
               <p>We have not only Gods repeated Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands prohibiting our familiarity with Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men, <note place="margin">Prov. 1.15. 4.14.23.20. Epheſ. 5.11 2 Theſ. 3.6.</note> but the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Saints againſt it, <note place="margin">2 Kings. 3.14. Jer. 15.17. 2 Chron. 19 2.20.37. Prov. 29.27</note> and Gods heavy Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments inflicted for it. But beſides theſe, it is impoſſible for Wicked Men directly and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to love a Chriſtian,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:109796:74"/> when there is no true love even among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And altho' theſe Swine and Bears do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times agree, it is not Peace, but Conſpiracy: and any the leaſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Profit, Luſt, or Pride, will preſently make them rage at, and devour one another. Man is to man, ſays Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Cowley,</hi> all kinds of Beaſts; a fawning Dog, a roaring Lion, a Thie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Fox, a diſſembling Crocodile, a treacherous Decoy, a rapacious Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: If then we would not periſh in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of Wicked men,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:109796:74"/> we muſt leave their Tents; <note place="margin">Numb. 16.26. Rev. 18.4.</note> and avoid being partakers of their Sins, as we deſire to be freed from their Plagues.</p>
               <p>Our Special and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Converſation muſt be with the wiſe and Virtuous: Eſpecially ſuch as fear God, not only for the Opinion of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who will ever judge us to be ſuch as our Company is; but for the benefit and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage we ſhall receive thereby.</p>
               <p>Think not thy ſelf too good to learn, even of the meaneſt Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>When thou ſpeakeſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:109796:75"/> of the things of God, be Humble, Reverend, and ſerious, keeping within the Line of thy Calling, and the Meaſure of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Grace given thee.</p>
               <p>Do not wreſt, and miſtake the Actions, Speeches, or Ends of good men: who, tho' they dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from thee in ſome Points, yet hold all ſuch as are neceſſary and fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental; rather indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour by all means to keep in the unity of the Spirit, by the bond of Peace. Nothing cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly brings more Joy, Comfort or Delight, next
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:109796:75"/> to the Communion with God in Chriſt, than the Actual Communion of Saints, and the love of the Brethren.</p>
               <p>Neither truſt any ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, that may indanger thy Eſtate or Perſon, with any Friend, or Servant, whatſoever. While thou art within thy ſelf, thou art ſafe; but thy Secret once ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd, makes thee a Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave to him thou truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and leaves thee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to his Mercy. 'Tis certain, never any man reveal'd a Secret of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, of which he did not afterwards re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent:
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:109796:76"/> For altho' he ſhould receive no damage there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, yet he can never free himſelf from diſquiet. How can a man aſſure himſelf his Friend will not diſcloſe that, which he himſelf (tho' it ſo nearly concern'd him) could not keep ſecret? The ſafeſt Rule is, ſo to carry thy ſelf to thy Friends, as perſons who may one day prove thy Enemies, and ſo to thy Enemies, as that thou mayeſt yet become their Friend.</p>
               <p>You ſhall never find a Friend in your young years, whoſe Conditions and Qualities will pleaſe
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:109796:76"/> thee after thou comeſt to more Diſcretion and Judgment: And then all thou haſt given is loſt, and all wherein thou haſt truſted ſuch a man, will be diſcover'd.</p>
               <p>Aſſociate thy ſelf with thy betters, at leaſt Peers. If thy Friend be of better Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity than thy ſelf, thou mayeſt be ſure he will be careful to keep thy Counſel; becauſe he has more to loſe than thou haſt; and again he will eſteem thee for thy ſelf, and not for what thou doſt poſſeſs. Yet remember always, that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:109796:77"/> thou never venture thy Eſtate with any of thoſe great ones as ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt unlawful things: for ſuch men labour for themſelves, and not for thee; thou ſhalt be ſure to partake with them in the danger, but not of the Advantage and Honour: and to venture a ſure Eſtate in preſent, in hope of a better in future, is meer madneſs. Beſides, Great men, when they have obtain'd their ends, forget ſuch as have done them Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and will rather hate thee, for ſaying thou haſt been a means
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:109796:77"/> of their advancement, than acknowledge it.</p>
               <p>Such as are thy Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, will follow thee but to eat thee up. If thou giveſt twenty gifts, and refuſe to do it but once, all thou haſt done will be loſt; and when thou leaveſt to feed them they will hate thee, and become thy mortal Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: Such kind of men the Rich may always have.</p>
               <p>Let thy Love there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be to the beſt, ſo long as they do well; but take heed that thou love God, thy Country, thy Prince, and thy own
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:109796:78"/> Eſtate, before all others; For the Fancies of men change; and he that loves thee to day, may hate thee to morrow.</p>
               <p>Obſerve the wiſe. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the honeſt. Love the Religious.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as Company is broke up, call thy ſelf to a ſtrict account; examine how far thou haſt hindred others, or preſerved thy ſelf from Evil; what good thou haſt either done, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd; what advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces thou haſt made, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Knowledge, or Virtue; and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let thy Heart either
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:109796:78"/> check, or comfort thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Art of making a man's Fortune.</head>
               <head type="sub">Moſtly out of my Lord <hi>Bacon.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THis Art chiefly conſiſts of two Points: A right know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of other men, and of a man's ſelf. A wiſe man ought to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe, and procure to himſelf a good informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, touching the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Perſons with whom he has to deal; their Natures, Deſires, Ends, and Cuſtoms; their Helps, and Advantages
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:109796:79"/> whereby they are chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſupported; their Weakneſſes, Diſadvanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and where they lye open, and are obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; their Friends, Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Patrons, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendencies; their Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, Enviers, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitors; their Modes, Times, and Critical ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Acceſs, and the Principal Rules they have ſet down to themſelves; to all which muſt be joyn'd a nice obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the particular Actions, which are on foot, from time to time, and as it were hot on the Anvil: For men
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:109796:79"/> change with the Action, and while they are inga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and inviron'd with buſineſs, they are one; when they return to their natures, quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſeveral ways the knowledge of men may be diſcloſed: By the Face and Countenance; certainly there can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be found ſo excellent a Diſſembler, or a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance ſo commanded and forced, that can ſever from an artificial Speech theſe Notes: It will ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be more Slight and careleſs, or more Set and formal; more
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:109796:80"/> Tedious and wandring, or more Dry and reluc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant than uſual.</p>
               <p>By their Words: which, tho' they be full of Flattery and Uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, yet theſe two ways may be excellently diſcover'd: When they are either utter'd upon the ſudden, or elſe in paſſion. There are few men ſo true to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and ſo ſetled in their Reſolves, but at ſom time or other, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of Heat or Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, Intimate good will to a Friend, Weakneſs, Trouble of Mind, or ſom other Paſſion, that
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:109796:80"/> can indure and hold out under theſe Weights and Tortures, without com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating and revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling their moſt inward thoughts: But above all, it ſounds the mind to the bottom, when ſimulation is put to it by a counter-diſſimulation, according to the Proverb. <hi>Tell a Lie, and finde a Truth.</hi> But this Rule belongs more to the States-man, than the Chriſtian, and ſhould indeed have its place among the Evil Rules.</p>
               <p>By mens Actions: Which, tho' the ſureſt pledges of mens Minds,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:109796:81"/> are not altogether to be truſted, without a Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and Judicious conſideration of their Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitude and Nature. The <hi>Italian</hi> thinks himſelf upon the Rack, when he is better uſed than he is wont to be without manifeſt cauſe: Small Favours do but lull men aſleep, both as to Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and as to Induſtry.</p>
               <p>But the ſureſt Key to unlock mens minds, is, to ſearch and diſcloſe either their Nature and Diſpoſitions, or their Ends and Intentions. The Weakeſt ſort of men, are beſt Interpreted by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:109796:81"/> their Natures; but the Wiſe, and more Reſerv'd are beſt expounded by their Ends: Yet cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly 'tis a frequent, and very familiar error with wiſe men, to over-ſhoot the Mark, meaſuring other men by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del of their own abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and ſuppoſing them to Project, and Deſign deeper Ends, and Prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice more ſubtil Arts, than ever came into their Heads. There is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly leſs Money, leſs Wiſdom, and leſs good Faith, than men do ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Princes, being at the top of Human de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:109796:82"/> and having for the moſt part no parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ends propounded to themſelves, whereto they aſpire, eſpecially with vehemence and perſeverance, are beſt Interpreted by their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
               <p>By Reports likewiſe we come to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of men: And here, Weakneſſes and Faults are beſt learnt from Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; Virtues and Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, from Friends; Cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oms and Times, from Servants; Thoughts and Opinions, from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate Confidents. Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Fame is light; and
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:109796:82"/> the Judgment of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors is uncertain: For before Such, men are Masked.</p>
               <p>But the moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious way is, to have general acquaintance and inwardneſs with ſuch men, as have moſt look'd into the World, and are well Verſed both in Men and Matters; but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to endeavour to have converſation and privacy with ſom par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Friend: who, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the diverſity of Buſineſs, and Perſons, is able to give us ſolid Information, and good In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligence of all Paſſages.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:109796:83"/>
               <p>That a man know himſelf, is a Rule of Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Prudence; and to do ſo, there is need of very frequent Inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſo often forget what manner of Perſons we are. Neither muſt this Examination be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial, ſuch a view as men, too much in love with themſelves, take but moſt ſtrict, and exact; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king account not only of our Abilities, Virtues, and Supports; but alſo of our own Defects, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abilities, and Impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; ever eſteeming Theſe with the moſt, Thoſe rather with the
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:109796:83"/> leaſt. This Politick Glaſs, wherein a man ſhould view himſelf, is nothing elſe, but the State of the World, and Times, in which we live.</p>
               <p>The firſt Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here ſhould be, How a man's Conſtitution and moral Temper ſorts with the general State of the Times: If they be found Agreeable, he may give himſelf more ſcope, and liberty; but if there be any Diſſonancy and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tipathy, then in the whole courſe of his Life he is to carry himſelf more cloſe and reſerv'd. The next conſideration
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:109796:84"/> is, How a man may be valued, and how he may deport himſelf, as he is compared with his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals and Rivals, whom it is likely he may have his Competitors; and that he take that courſe of life, where there is the greateſt ſolitude of able men, and himſelf like to be moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
               <p>And in the laſt place: A man ought to take heed how he guides him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by Examples, and that he do not fondly affect the Imitation of others, without due con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:109796:84"/> there may be between the Perſons he has choſe for his Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns and Examples in their Natures, Perſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For that may be Graceful and Fit for them to do, which in him may ſeem Ridiculous; and what they may eaſily accompliſh by reaſon of the ſutableneſs of their natures and tempers, he (tho' having the ſame opportunities) ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring about.</p>
               <p>Nor is the right un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of a Man's ſelf ſufficient; there are other things likewiſe to be regarded: As firſt,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:109796:85"/> a man muſt conſult with himſelf upon a way, how wiſely to open and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal himſelf. It is a great advantage, if a man can, by a kind of Art and Grace, ſet himſelf forth to others, aptly revealing without diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſt or arrogance his Virtues, Merits, or For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; for tho' Wiſe and Solemn men may ſmile at this, and deſpiſe it, yet ſure it will take with the more Ignorant and Vulgar: and the eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of many will coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervail the diſdain of a few. Certainly not a few, more ſolid than
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:109796:85"/> windy natures, have ſuffer'd great prejudice and diſadvantage, in point of Reputation and Merit, for want of this Art of bearing up ſail in the heights of the Wind.</p>
               <p>But the Covering of Weakneſſes, Misfortunes, and Diſgraces, is of no leſs importance, than the dextrous and wiſe O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtentation of Virtues. Defects are conceal'd by a threefold induſtry, and as it were under three Coverts; Caution, Colour, and Confidence. Caution, is, when we do wiſey avoid being
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:109796:86"/> put upon thoſe things, for which we are not proper; the great er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of bold, and unſtay'd Spirits, who thereby publiſh all their Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. Colour is, when we do warily and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make way to have a favourable conſtruction made of our Faults and Wants, as proceeding from a better cauſe, or intended for ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſe, than is generally conceived: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring ſtill to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our defects, by bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowing and putting on the Colour of the next bordering Virtues, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:109796:86"/> they may be ſhadow'd. But the moſt ſure and effectual Remedy is, that a man profeſs to deſpiſe what he cannot attain. There is another kind of Confidence yet more impudent, which is to out-face a man's own defects; to boaſt and obtrude them upon O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion: and to help this again, and that the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception put upon others may come off more roundly, he may feign that he had the leaſt O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of himſelf in thoſe things wherein he is beſt; but there is nothing, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails a man more or,
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:109796:87"/> puts a fairer gloſs upon him, than that he do not expoſe his Perſon to ſcorn or injury, but right himſelf in all points, in all things ſhewing ſom ſparkles, and edge of a Free and Generous Spirit, that carries with it as well a Sting as Hony, keeping always a fortify'd carriage, a prompt and prepar'd re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution to vindicate him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from ſcorn.</p>
               <p>A wiſe man ought to indeavour by all poſſible means to bend and mould his mind, that it may become pliant and obedient to Occaſions
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:109796:87"/> and Opportunities; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hinders the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting of Buſineſs, and making a man's Fortune, more, than when men are where they were, and follow their old bent, when Occaſions are tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</p>
               <p>We ſhould inure our minds to Judge of the proportion and value of things, as they conduce more or leſs to our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, and the ends we intend.</p>
               <p>A man ought to look about him on all ſides, and obſerve where things are open, where ſhut, where eaſy, and where
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:109796:88"/> difficult to be compaſs'd; and never to overſtrain, or miſemploy his ſtrength, where the way is not paſſable.</p>
               <p>We muſt not always expect Occaſion, but ſomtimes provoke it: A wiſe man makes more Occaſions, than be ſinds. We may obſerve in the managing of Affairs, and handling Buſineſs, two kinds of ſufficiencies: For ſom can make uſe of Occaſions aptly and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly, but can Plot and excogitate nothing; others, are all for Plots, which they can well urge and purſue, but
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:109796:88"/> cannot accommodate. Each of theſe is imperfect, without the other: We ought therefore to have an eye to our Natures, and Tempers in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na gery of Buſineſe; to know what we are moſt fit for, and not willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ingage in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, which tho' we have never ſo many Oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities for, we ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring about.</p>
               <p>A man, that would make his Fortune, ought never to embrace any matters which take up too great a quantity of time. The cauſe why thoſe who addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:109796:89"/> to Profeſſions of Burden, as Lawyers, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, Writers of Books, and the like, are not commonly ſo Politick in contriving and promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their own Fortunes, is no other than this, They want time, which is otherwiſe employ'd, to inform themſelves of particulars, to wait u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon Occaſions, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and project Deſigns, which may conduce to the making of them.</p>
               <p>But after all this, we ought not to be ſo Weak and Fooliſh, as to imagin, that Fortunes are not to be obtain'd without all
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:109796:89"/> this ado; for we know well that they come tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling into ſome mens laps, and a number ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain very good ones in a plain way, without any great or painful Art, only by Diligence, Aſſiduity, and a little Caution intermingled.</p>
               <p>In this hot race af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Fortune, to cool our ſelves a little, let us call to mind that elegant conceipt, That Fortune has ſomething of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Woman; if ſhe be too much woo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſhe is the farther off. But the beſt direction is, that we harken to
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:109796:90"/> what Divinity and Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy both teach us ſhould be firſt ſought after: Our Saviour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands us, <hi>That we ſeek firſt the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and the Righteouſneſs thereof; and all other things ſhall be ſuper-ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> And Philoſophy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyns ſomwhat like this. <hi>Seek firſt the goods of the mind, and the reſt ſhall be ſupplyed, or thou no way prejudiced by their abſence.</hi> Theſe are ſom of thoſe, which they call good Arts: As for the evil ones, tho' we ought not to make uſe of them our ſelves, yet
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:109796:90"/>
'tis not amiſs to infert a few of them; that we may know by what Rules ſom men act, and by what Rules they judge other men move.</p>
               <p>As firſt, Diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or Detraction, Diſtruſt or Suſpicion, Compliance or Neutra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, Reſervedneſs or Cloſeneſs, Surpriſal or Advantage, Irreligion or Atheiſm.</p>
               <p>The Politician need not much care for Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue it ſelf, but only for the Appearance and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of it in the Eyes of the World: Becauſe the Fame and Credit of
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:109796:91"/> it is a help, but the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance hurts; and the uſe of it is a Cumber. He muſt by all means make the moſt inſinuating applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the People, that he can; and lock up his owne Deſigns under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence for Religion, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Reſtitution of Laws, Reformation of Cabals and evil Counſellors, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of State &amp;c. If the Supremacy be invaded, the lapſes of the Former Magiſtrate muſt be incul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated with the greateſt advantage: What is wanting in reality, muſt be ſupply'd with Calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. He muſt hire mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenary
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:109796:91"/> Jeſuits, or other Divines, to cry up his ayms, in the Churches; that ſo the Poiſon may inſinuate more general<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into all the parts. If ſucceſs awaits his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes, he muſt urge it to Authenticate his Cauſe. He ought to change with the times. If he find rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to impoſe Oaths, let them be of ſuch ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guity, as may furniſh with a Senſe obliging to the Deſign; and yet ſo ſoft, as the People may not feel the ſmart. Neceſſity of State is a very competent Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy for the worſt of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:109796:92"/> He muſt wave all Relations, both Sacred and Civil; and Swim to his Deſign tho' in a Sea of Blood. A gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Innovation contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes much to the growth and ſecurity of Uſurpation. He ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that men are not rightly and ſafely to be wrought upon, and bow'd to the Bent of his will, otherwiſe than by Fear; and therefore he indeavours by all means poſſible to have every man obnoxious, low, and in ſtreights. His Maximes are, <hi>Cadant amici, dummodo inimici
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:109796:92"/> intercidant,</hi> as the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umviri ſold the lives of their Friends, for the death of their Enemies. <hi>If once a Fire ſeize upon his Fortune, he will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh it not with Water, but with Ruin. Men are to be deceiv'd with Oaths.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>With ſuch corrupt, and pernicious Arts and Poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions as theſe, and others of the ſame Impreſſion, (whereof as in all other things the evil are more in number, than the good and ſound) a man may be more ſpeedy and compendious in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting his Fortune: But it is in Life, as in Ways,
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:109796:93"/> the ſhorteſt way is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the fouleſt; and ſurely the faireſt way is not much about. Men ought therefore in the purſuit of Fortune, to ſet before their Eyes, not only that general Map of the whole World. That <hi>All things are Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Vexation of Spirit;</hi> But alſo that more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Card and Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, That <hi>Being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Well being is a Curſe, and that all Virtue is moſt rewarded, and all Wickedneſs is moſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd, in its ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:109796:93"/>
               <head>Of Recreation, and Pleaſure.</head>
               <p>IT is one chief point of Wiſdom, to know how to temper our Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and Sorrows: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents will Vary; if We continue the ſame, it matters not. Let us learn then, by a juſt ſurvey, to know the due and lawful bounds of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and then neither, to go beyond, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move them. Be acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Quality of Pleaſure, and the Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure: many have loſt themſelves in a Lawful
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:109796:94"/> delight, through exceſs. Could we ſettle in our ſelves a right eſtimati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that wherein we delight, and reſolve e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thing into it's firſt matter, there would be more danger of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, than overjoy. What is the Human Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, whoſe beauty we ſo admire, but the ſame Earth we tread upon? What thoſe precious Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals we Worſhip, but Veins of the Earth bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter colour'd? and if we look to their end, we ſhall ſee Laughter end in Tears, and Death; and Conſcience ſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:109796:94"/> with a long ſmart for a ſhort pleaſure.</p>
               <p>In Recreations we are to obſerve all due Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances: they muſt be Decent, becoming our Perſon, Place, and Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. They muſt be ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, at ſuch times as are allotted, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd by God unto them: Pleaſures muſt ever give place to Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and none of our Buſineſs muſt be loſt for Sport. They ought to be taken as Phyſick, or at leaſt as Wine; our Love and Affections muſt not fix and faſten upon them: for then
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:109796:95"/> they will not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume too much of our time, but our Hearts will be unſetled, and our Affections wean'd from Religious. Exerciſes. When our ſports come to that exceſs, that we tempt others, and hunt, and long for Opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; when we ſit up till midnight, and ſpend half days, then we have ſpoil'd the ſport; 'Tis no longer a Recreation, but a Sin.</p>
               <p>All our Recreations muſt be without Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal: neither uſing ſuch before others, at which they have any Scruple;
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:109796:95"/> or any unſeemly light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Vanity, or Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in them.</p>
               <p>Our Recreations ought not to be too coſtly: not only conſidering, how many empty Bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, and naked Backs, how many diſtreſſed Members of the ſame Body cry to us, even with tears of Blood, for Relief and compaſſion from our abundance: but the great and exact Account we muſt e're long give of every Far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, how we got it, how we ſpent it, with what Warrant we kept it.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:109796:96"/>
               <p>A good man ought not, for Recreation ſake, to conſort himſelf with evil Company: <note place="margin">Ephe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 5.</note> Nothing cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes more Friendly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance and Familia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, nothing ſooner breeds likeneſs of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and conditions, than agreement and commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the ſame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights: From liking the Pleaſure, we come to like our Companion in, it, and from affecting the Man, we come at laſt to affect his Manners.</p>
               <p>Recreation is to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed as a Liberal Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and not as a ſordid Trade: Gameing is an
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:109796:96"/> inordinate Courſe, which God never appointed, nor bleſt, to get Wealth; and ſo is no better, nay rather worſe than com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Theft; in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing committed by mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual agreement, the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer becomes acceſſory to the Theft of the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and is, as well as he, not only a Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of himſelf, but of his Family; making both ſad and poor, becauſe the Dice turn up an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucky Chance.</p>
               <p>In all our Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons we muſt take care that we forget not God, and be not <hi>lovers of
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:109796:97"/> Pleaſure, more than lovers of Him,</hi> Iſa. 5.12. 2 Tim. 3.4. And then when our Pleaſures exclude not the preſence of God, nor the fruition of him; when we have his Bleſſing on them, and uſe them without dotage, as in God, from God, and to God, we are ſafe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Evening Exerciſes.</head>
               <p>HAving thus walk'd with God, from Morning untill Night, it remains that we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude the Day with him. Evening therefore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:109796:97"/> now come, no Tradeſman ſhould be more careful to clear his Shop-board, and ſhut up his Windows, than we ſhould be to ſhut up our Thoughts, and clear our Minds. That man ſhall live miſerably, who, like a Camel, lies down under his burden. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore therefore thou go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to thy reſt, retire thy ſelf a little; and, having finiſh'd thy courſe of Reading, ſit down, and take a ſtrict view of thy whole car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage the day paſt: look back, and call Orderly to thy mind the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:109796:98"/> places and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies thou haſt been in the day paſt; and how thou haſt carry'd thy ſelf in each; examin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thy ſelf by thy Thoughts and Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, by thy Words and Actions. For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, calling thy ſelf to account, ſay, Thus much time was ſpent this day in ſuch a place: Did any Lie drop from me there? Any corrupt, unſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, raſh, and unſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Diſcourſe? Did no unruly Paſſion break out? Were my Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons holy and humble,
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:109796:98"/> and my heart chaſt and pure? My Behaviour Wiſe, and Courteous, becoming my Place and Perſon, while I was there? Thus thou may'ſt run through the whole Day.</p>
               <p>In the next place, conſider your Religious Duties, and carriage in them; Your Calling, and how you have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd the Duties be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to that; your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and carriage to them, As a Husband, Wife, Parent, Child, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, Servant; Your particular Corruptions, and the Sins you are
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:109796:99"/> moſt inclin'd to; toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and how you have behaved your ſelf in reference to them; Your Talents, whether you have waſted and miſpent, or improv'd and employ'd them for the end they were giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en; Your Providences, what they have been, and how you have, and ought to have carry'd your ſelf under them. In ſhort, whether you have lived by Faith, that is, have fram'd your Life according to the revealed Will of God, the Object of Faith:
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:109796:99"/> and whether you have been conſtant to your own Rules?</p>
               <p>Having thus exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min'd your ſelf, Reform that which you find a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſs: Rejoice, or be griev'd, as you find you have done well or ill; and renew and confirm your peace with God; committing thy Spirit, Soul, and Body, thy Relations, Name, and Subſtance, to his Tuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Prayer and Thankſgiving, who a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone can keep thee in ſafety.</p>
               <p>By this daily exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of our Selves,
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:109796:100"/> we gain theſe two great Advantages: Firſt, Our Repentance will hereby be more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, not only of cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous and more cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sins, but multitudes of other particulars; eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry branch and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of every Action, every Word, Thought, and Affection, many Sins which otherwiſe would have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got, will by this means be brought to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, and repented of by us. And again, when ever Death ſeizes us, we ſhall have but one day of our whole Life to Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count for.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="189" facs="tcp:109796:100"/>
               <head>The Chriſtian Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe, taken out of a Learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine.</head>
               <p>TO keep the Heart in ure with God, is the higheſt Task of a Chriſtian. Good mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are not frequent; but the conſtancy of good Diſpoſition is rare, and hard: This work muſt be continual, or elſe ſpeedeth not. If this Field be not Till'd every day, it will run out into Thiſtles. The evening is the fitteſt for this work, when retir'd
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:109796:101"/> into our Selves, we chearfully, and conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both look up to God, and into our Hearts, as we have to do with both.</p>
               <p>To God, in Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, then in Requeſt. It ſhall be therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for the Soul du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to recount to it ſelf all the ſpecialities of God's favour. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed thanks ſavours of careleſneſs, and neither doth affect us, nor win acceptance above. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think your ſelf then of all theſe External, Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, Earthly Graces and Favours; That your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:109796:101"/> Breathing, Life, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Reaſon, is from him: and that he hath given you a more no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Nature, than the reſt of the Creatures, excellent Faculties of the Mind, perfection of Senſes, ſoundneſs of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, competency of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, ſeemlineſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, fitneſs of Calling, preſervation from Dang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, reſcue out of Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, kindneſs of Friends, carefulneſs of Education, honeſty of Reputation, liberty of Recreations, quietneſs of Life, oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of Well-doing, protection of Angels:
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:109796:102"/> Then riſe higher, to your Spiritual Favours, tho here on Earth, and ſtrive to raiſe your Affections with your Thoughts. Bleſs God that you were born in the light of the Goſpel, for your Profeſſion of the Truth, for the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of your Vocation, for your incorporating into the Church, for the priviledge of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>craments, the free uſe of the Scriptures, the Communion of Saints, the benefit of their Prayers; the aid of their Counſel, the example of their Lives, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:109796:102"/> of their Converſion; for the beginnings of Regeneration, any foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps of Faith, Hope, Love, Zeal, Patience, Humility, Peace, Joy for any deſire of more. Then let your Soul mount higheſt of all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Heaven, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thoſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Graces of her E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection to Glory; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption from ſhame and Death; of the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of our Saviour; of the preparation of her place; and there let her ſtay a while, upon the Meditation of her future Joyes.</p>
               <pb n="194" facs="tcp:109796:103"/>
               <p>This done, the way is made for your Requeſts. Sue now to your God, as for Grace to anſwer theſe Mercies, ſo to ſee wherein you have not anſwer'd them. From him therefore caſt your Eyes down upon your ſelf; and as ſome careful Juſtice doth a ſuſpected Felon, ſo do you ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly examin your heart of what you have done that Day, of what you ſhould have done: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, whether your thoughts have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſterd to God, Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers to the World, fix'd on Heaven? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:109796:103"/> Juſt, Charitable, Lowly, Pure, Chriſtian? whether your Senſes have been holily guided, neither to let in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, nor to let out Sins? whether your Speeches have not been Offenſive, Vain, Raſh, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet, Unſavory, Une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difying? whether your Actions have been war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable, expedient, comely, profitable? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have perform'd the particular Dutyes of the day, in your A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waking, Refreſhing, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, Company, Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures? then ſee if you have been negligent in
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:109796:104"/> watching your Heart, expence of your time, exerciſes of Devotion, performance of good Works, reſiſtance of tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, good uſe of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, and compare your preſent State with your former, look Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly, whether your Soul hath gain'd or loſt, loſt ought of the heat of her Love, tenderneſs of Conſcience, fear to Offend, ſtrength of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; gain'd more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace, more aſſurance of Glory: And when you find (Alas! who cannot but find?) either Holineſs decay'd,
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:109796:104"/> or Evil done, or Good omitted; caſt down your Eyes, ſtrike your Breaſts, humble your Soul, and ſigh to him whom you have Offended, ſue for Pardon, as for Life, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, yearningly, injoyn your ſelf careful amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, redouble your holy Reſolutions, ſtrike hands with God in a new Covenant, my ſoul for your ſafety.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Rules for the Night.</head>
               <p>THERE's not a moment of our time our own: The Night brings it's Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:109796:105"/> as well as the Day. This is a proper Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for Meditation and Prayer; as appears by the many Inſtances we have in Scripture; Both of <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 42.8. <hi>The Lord will command his loving kindneſs in the Day-time; and in the Night, his Songs ſhall be with me, and my Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er unto the God of my life:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 6.9. Cant. 3.1.</note> And of the Church. But 'tis then eſpecially our Duty, when we are under any heavy and ſore Affliction, in deep Humiliation, or in Suits of great Importance, which we would ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:109796:105"/> with the greateſt earneſtneſs and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity: <note place="margin">Coloſ. 4.2. 1 Pet. 4.7. 2 Sam. 12.16. Eſt. 4.3. 1 Kings 2.27. Joel 1.13.</note> In ſuch Caſes, it has been an ancient Cuſtom for the Servants of God to abſtain from their ordinary Sleep, that ſo they might watch unto Prayer.</p>
               <p>As to Dreams, tho they are not much to be regarded, in reſpect of any gueſs can be made by them, yet we are not utterly to neglect them; becauſe we may gain thereby ſome know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our Body, our natural diſpoſitions, and the Sins to which we
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:109796:106"/> are moſt inclin'd; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that ſaying, <hi>The Night ſhall teach me what I am; the Day, what I ſhould be.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Sleep.</head>
               <p>IT is as impoſſible to give a conſtant and certain Rule for Sleep, as to preſcribe the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Meats and Drinks: Tho we may as well Surfeit and Sin in the one, as in the other. Nor is the exceſs of Sleep without its parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular evils; being hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to Soul, Body, and Eſtate: It robs us of
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:109796:106"/> the chief and principal part of our time, the prime of the morning, and makes the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der leſs Serviceable, by weakening our Body, which by moderate reſt is refreſh'd and ſtren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then'd; and making us heavy, lazy, and dull, both leſs able, and leſs active in any em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. It improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes the Eſtate, as wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> tells us, <note place="margin">Prov. 6.11. 13.4. 20.4. 23.21.</note> and brings the Soul alſo to Beggery, and want of all ſaving Grace; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king us either utterly to neglect, or elſe to ſhorten and hurry over
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:109796:107"/> our ſpiritual Exerciſe; excuſing our Selves with the importunity of our Affairs, and the ſcanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our Time, tho' our voluntary Sloth has brought us into theſe Streights.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Temptations.</head>
               <p>DIvines uſually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations into Three ſorts: Aſcendent, or ſuch as riſe, or fume up from ſome ſtirred humour, or lower faculty within us, that borders next upon Senſe, or Affection. Objected, or ſuch as
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:109796:107"/> reflect from ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward object, baited, and ſuted to the Organs. Injected, or ſuch as the Tempter immediately affects the faculty it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with. The danger lies eſpecially in the two firſt: As to the third, the Devil can do little more, than Trouble in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of Tempt. Our Saviour tells us, that <hi>the Wicked one came and found nothing in him,</hi> and ſo could fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten nothing on him: And his Apoſtle tells us, <hi>if we could keep our ſelves, the wicked One could not hurt us<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 14.30.</note> His
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:109796:108"/> power, however great, is limited. It ſeems lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſs than an invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of God's prerogative, and giving the Devil more than his due, to allow him a power of immediate, and impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive injection into our minds, without the help of Object, Organ, low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Faculty, or innate Corruption of our own.</p>
               <p>There is not one hour of our Life, in which we do not converſe with ſome Temptation or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; nor any condition, without its peculiar Temptations. In lawful Actions, we are ſubject
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:109796:108"/> to the Temptation of immoderateneſs, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs: In Religious, to Formality, and Vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glory: In Proſperity to pride and forgetfulneſs of God, luxury, intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance and contempt of others: in Adverſity, to unlawful means, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring, diſcontent, and accuſing Providence: under Injuries, to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiveneſs and immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Anger: Under Comforts, to ſecurity, abatement of Love to God, and ſetting up our reſt and hope in this preſent World: In Knowledge, to vain and
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:109796:109"/> impertinent curioſity, pride, and ſelf-conceit: In Sickneſs, to impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: In Health, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and forgetful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of our latter end: In our Callings, either to negligence, unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and idleneſs; or elſe to overmuch ſolicitouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and vexation. In Company, we are in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of being miſguided by evil perſwaſion, and the example of others: If Alone, we are apt to be corrupted by evil ſuggeſtions, either of our own hearts, or of Satan. We ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore earneſtly to beg of
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:109796:109"/> God, to preſerve us from being overcome by the Temptations, that do un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably occur in all Actions and Conditions; and that he would ſhew us the danger we are in, through the multitude, power, and ſubtlety of our Enemies; and the vileneſs of our own na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which runs after Satans allurements, and conſpires with him to its own perdition: and we ſhould alſo frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly every day reflect with our ſelves, what ſort of Temptations at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent we are moſt obnoxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to: what are moſt
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:109796:110"/> likely to aſſault us, and how we are to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand them.</p>
               <p>A man may reſiſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Temptation of the Devil, if he do but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and purely will it, without any mixture of unwillingneſs: But to make ſuch a reſiſtance, is impoſſible of a mans ſelf, or from any natural Power in him; but from the gift of God, and the help and aſſiſtance of his Grace; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Gifts of Graces and Virtues, the Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Protection of God is neceſſary for Believers, that they may
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:109796:110"/> reſiſt Temptations: and likewiſe thoſe manifold helps wherewith God ſuccours his Elect. The firſt of theſe helps, is the driving away the Enemy; whereby he is not ſuffer'd ſometimes to tempt the Elect. <note place="margin">Job. 1.</note> The ſecond is, the bridling him in; not ſuffering him to tempt ſo much as he would. <note place="margin">Job. 2.</note> The third, from the Tempter him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when ever the ſhape under which he tempts, affords ſome help of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: So the form of the Serpent might have caus'd <hi>Eve</hi> to have ſuſpected. The fourth
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:109796:111"/> from the Temptation it ſelf: When it either ſtirs up Fear in us, which is the beſt Keeper; or ſtirs us up to fight, and incourages us againſt the Enemy. The fifth, new Grace, or increaſe of the former. <note place="margin">Math. 25 Luke. 19.</note> The Sixth, a Ceſſation, Peace, or rather Truce from the Temptation. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth, Refreſhment in the heat of Temptation, as when the Tribulation is turn'd into a Solace. The eighth, a Strength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Comforting, and Lifting up the Heart by a promiſe of ſtrength and Victory; with a
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:109796:111"/> Demonſtration of the weakneſs of the Enemy. The ninth, a Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or chearing the Heart, in Troubles, ſorrows, and Grief, The tenth, a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowing Faith and Hope, and confirmation of the ſame, againſt the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Fear, which ariſes from our own defect and Infirmities.</p>
               <p>Again; firſt an up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding them that are ſet upon, that they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive no hurt, tho' they are ſore aſſaulted oft, times, that they are even ready to fall; that they may acknowledge their own Infirmities, and
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:109796:112"/> aſcribe it to God's Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, not their own Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that they are kept. Secondly, God's relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of them that fly to him; in which reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect he is call'd, the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place of the Elect. Thirdly, God's fighting againſt, and overthrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Enemy. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Outward Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of which there are many profits this way. Fifthly, the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Laſt things: Death, Judgment, Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and Happineſs.</p>
               <p>It is very difficult to overcome Temptations, becauſe no man fights
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:109796:112"/> with all his Strength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt any one. A Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever in Temptation, is like a Kingdom divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded within it ſelf; like an Arm'd Horſeman, that Sits upon a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, unruly, and unbro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Colt; like a ſtout War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, upon a Slippery Pavement.</p>
               <p>Amongſt the Moſt hidden Treacheries, and moſt ſubtile Temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Devil, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the moſt wiſe and valiant Chriſtians, are oftentimes overcome; the firſt is long, and tedious, whereby he wearies them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:109796:113"/> deavours to bring them not only into the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but into Deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration alſo, and a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that they belong not to God, that God cares not for them. This great Miſchief ariſes from the Ignorance of that good, which may be obtain'd by a long, and a frequent Combating with Temptation: It ſerves for the breaking of Pride, for the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring other Infirmities, which elſe would never have been ſeen, and for the preſervation of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility. Secondly the ſtrangeneſs of the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation,
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:109796:113"/> and the unuſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alneſs of it; ſo that a man becomes fearful, whether he belongs to God, becauſe he cannot hear of any, that have been Tempted in the ſame ſort. The third ſubtilty is, when the Devil indeavours to make a man change that State wherein he is, and wherein he is well: As Birds and Fiſhes are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, by noiſe and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, driven from the Places in which they were ſafe, into the Snares of the Fowler. The fourth, when he invites a man to thoſe things
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:109796:114"/> which are above his ſtrength. The fifth, when under pretence of ſome Good, he draws a man into Danger; and, under pretence of Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, perſwades a man to ſome Vice. The ſixth is a Peace and Ceſſation from Temptation; the moſt dangerous ſubtlety of all: for from hence ſprings Sloth, Pride, Contempt of our Brethren, Hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Heart, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A man may reſiſt Temptation three ways. Firſt, he reſiſts, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents not: The Tempter is overcome, if he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come not. Secondly, he
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:109796:114"/> reſiſts Temptations, that flies from, and ſhuns Them. Thirdly, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, which beats them back, and makes oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>With the ſhunning Temptation, we muſt joyn Indignation, not vouchſafing to look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, or harken to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, what ever he offers; contemning and ſcor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when he offers that which is infinitely leſs worth, and even nothing, in compariſon of God's Love. Here is the great Point of Wiſdom, and Spiritual skill, ſo fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently to love God, ſo
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:109796:115"/> cloſely to cleave to him, ſo diligently to employ one's ſelf to do his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to preſerve and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend Virtue, and to be ſo immovably fix'd in theſe Exerciſes, that the Darts of Temptation may not touch us.</p>
               <p>A temptation is beſt beaten back by its own Weapon: Now every Virtue does ſo, as often as in the Temptation, its Beauty and pretiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is ſeriouſly thought upon; for by ſuch Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, both the Sins, that do Tempt us, and and the thoughts, that
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:109796:115"/> proceed from them, are always weakned, and ſometimes vaniſh into no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, as Darkneſs flies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, when Light approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; for the only reaſon that Vice, and the Profits and Pleaſures thereof, ſeem in the hour of Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to have ſome Excellency, and be of ſome Value and Worth, is, becauſe at the time the Law and Light of Virtue is hid from our Eyes, either through Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance or Negligence; as rotten Wood, and the Scales of Fiſhes, do ſhine in the Night, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the light of the
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:109796:116"/> Sun, and other lights, are wanting.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Self-Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>THE neceſſity of this ſelf-reflexion appears from this double conſideration: the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the neglect, and the great benefit of the Practice of this Duty.</p>
               <p>The neglect of it, makes a man a ſtranger to himſelf: (A very dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous fault, yet very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily run into, through the Love of Sin and ones ſelf) it throws a man every
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:109796:116"/> moment upon a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand unexpected dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; and who can tell how wicked he ſhall be, that does not know how bad he is? And when once God ſhall awaken a mans Conſcience, and tear off the covering, wherewith Sloth and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity have muffled it, when by ſome notable Judgment or Sickneſs, he ſhall quicken in a Man the remembrance of his former Iniquities, and ſummon him to Death, and Judgment; when he ſhall ſee his Sins ſet in order before him, and large Rolls
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:109796:117"/> of Indictments written againſt him, full of his Sins and Woes, within and without; Oh! in what a maze, in what a miſerable condition, is ſuch a Perſon!</p>
               <p>As to the benefit, that comes by this Practice. Hereby a man ſhall come to the knowledge of himſelf, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Eſtate; ſhall ſee what Graces he has, and what thoſe are, he moſt wants: It will diſcover the whole temper of his Soul, and ſhew him what evil Affections are ſtrongeſt in him, and in what things he is moſt
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:109796:117"/> apt to Sin; what Graces are weakeſt in him, what moſt uſeful for him, that he may the more ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly implore them. And beſides, this parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular knowledge will bring forth theſe three bleſſed effects.</p>
               <p>Watchfulneſs, and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of Conſcience. He that is acquainted with the State of his Body, and knows what is hurtful, what is healthful, and what the danger of a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit, or any other Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is, will be very wary of his Diet, and courſe of Life: Nature teaches this; and, ſurely Grace
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:109796:118"/> is a better Inſtructer He that has taken tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough notice of the great Diſtempers of his Heart, how ſuddenly he is trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with Paſſion, how quickly intic'd by every Temptation to practice any evil; that had ſeen, how ugly and fearful the face of Sin is, when preſented in its true ſhape, and ſtript of all its lying Pleaſures and Profits, and accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny'd only with God's hatred and Curſe; that has found, what it is to venture upon Sin, what the loſs of Gods Favour, the joy of the Holy
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:109796:118"/> Ghoſt, the peace and quiet of a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is: blame not that man if he be afraid to Sin.</p>
               <p>Humility. He that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten beholds himſelf in the unſpotted Glaſs of Gods Law, will not be very forward to fall in love with his own beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: When a man ſits down to try himſelf by the Law of God, he finds therein all perfections of Holineſs commanded, but not the thouſand part of it in himſelf: he reads long Catalogues of Sins forbidden, upon pain of Gods eternal diſpleaſure;
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:109796:119"/> and in his own Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, he finds the Guilt of all, or moſt of thoſe Tranſgreſſions. When he ſcans his beſt Works, he finds they fall ſhort of that Faith, Zeal, Since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and perfect Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, wherein they ought to have been perform'd; he finds that he has little whereof to be proud: much whereof to be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: So that, what ever others may think of him, he knows, ſo much evil, and ſo little good by himſelf, that he cannot have high thoughts of himſelf: Let him be deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſed, reviled, or reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched,
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:109796:119"/> as baſe and vile; it is no Corroſive to him: he abhors himſelf more, than any other can deſpiſe him; and is more Vile in his own Eſteem, than he can be in theirs.</p>
               <p>True Peace and Comfort. He that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten calls himſelf to a ſtrict Account, that Judges himſelf for his Tranſgreſſions, weeping over them with godly Sorrow, never ceaſing till pardon be obtain'd: this man alone poſſeſſes his Heart in peace and comfort, and can with great quietneſs and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, expect the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:109796:120"/> of all Adverſity nothing can put ſuch a man to much fear or trouble, neither Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor Sickneſs, nor Death, nor Judgment it ſelf.</p>
               <p>This is the benefit of this Exerciſe; and yet how great a ſhame it is to conſider our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and careleſneſs, who ſeek to know All things, but our Selves? Our minds are like our Eyes, we can turn neither of them inward. Oh! therefore for the furture let us take all oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunities that ſhall be of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd; we are not at all
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:109796:120"/> times alike diſpos'd for this Exerciſe; there are ſpecial occaſions that fit us for it: many times one ſad accident or other turns home our thoughts to our Selves, and makes us ſee what we are in other men: The loſs of a dear Friend, the ſound of a Paſſing-bell, the ſight of a Dying man, have a ſtrange Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue many times to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe a diſorder'd Heart. Sometimes a Sermon has ſet us to rights, and ſent us home quicken'd with much holy Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; ſometimes a Fit of natural Melancholy
<pb n="230" facs="tcp:109796:121"/> and Penſiveneſs makes us apt for inward ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation; ſometimes a wakeful Bed calls upon us to examine our hearts: many ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions God offers, if we were either Wiſe to ſee, or Willing to make uſe of them.</p>
               <p>But if opportunities do not offer themſelves, we ſhould make them: A Wiſe man makes more, than he finds. Spare an hour in a Week, one day in a Month, for this buſineſs; Say not, thou haſt a Calling to mind; many buſineſſes, that require thy preſence,
<pb n="231" facs="tcp:109796:121"/> and diligence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can'ſt not mind all; Intend thou the chiefeſt, and that is Religion: Theſe are good indeed in their time and place; This only of abſolute ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity.</p>
               <p>The Subject of our Tryal ſhould be our whole Man: Whether we find the change, that is, the New brith, begun in us?</p>
               <p>Our mind, whether we labour to be daily more enlighten'd, to know that which is good and to be embrac'd; and that which is evil for to be avoided, by increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="232" facs="tcp:109796:122"/> in the knowledg of the Word, and eſpecially of Jeſus Chriſt and him Crucified, reveal'd in the ſame?</p>
               <p>Our Memory, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it do more firmly keep thoſe good things, that it has learned?</p>
               <p>Our Will, whether it more freely chuſe the good, and refuſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, and ſo be daily more pliant and obedient to the will of the Lord?</p>
               <p>Our Affections, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be every day more conform'd to the holineſs of Chriſt: that is, in loving that, which God loves; hating that,
<pb n="233" facs="tcp:109796:122"/> which he hates; rejoic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in that, whereby he is honour'd and well pleaſed, grieving for the contrary; fearing only the offending of him, ſecuring our ſelves in his love and favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone?</p>
               <p>Our Conſcience, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be ſtill tender; Checking us for every fault done, or intended; Quieting us in this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance, That our Sins are waſh'd away in the Blood of Chriſt. Bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Witneſs unto us of our upright lives and converſations, at leaſt begun: with a reſolute
<pb n="234" facs="tcp:109796:123"/> purpoſe ſo to proceed all our dayes?</p>
               <p>Our Body, whether it indeavour after more ability daily, to perform every Duty accordingly, and in every part, and all this at all times, and in all places convenient?</p>
               <p>Finally, we are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our whole Life or converſation, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ewe feel a change therein unto newneſs of Life? All theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord's, he does require this holineſs in them all; and that by ſtriving to perfection, each day to grown a little, until we come to
<pb n="235" facs="tcp:109796:123"/> a perfect man, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the age of the fulneſs of Chriſt: Until we fell ſuch a change in ſome meaſure, we can never have any true comfort.</p>
               <p>Again, we are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine our Faith, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be true, or no? <note place="margin">Revel. 22.17. John 7.37.</note> Saving Faith is never without its Grounds, which are God's free proffer. <note place="margin">John 6.40. 2 Cor. 5.20. 1 Joh. 3.23. and 5.10.</note> His Will, and Deſire; his Command and Promiſe. <note place="margin">Joh. 6.36.</note> It has ever ſome Word, or Writing from God, to ſhew for that which it believes. It will make one willing to try it ones
<pb n="236" facs="tcp:109796:124"/> ſelf, and willing any body elſe ſhould try it, yea God himſelf. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.5. Pſal. 139.23.</note> Where ſaving Faith is, there will be a Spiritual Strug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and Conflict; not between the Conſcience convinc'd, and the Will, as was in <hi>Pilate;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">John. 19.12. &amp;. 16.</note> But between the Regenerate and Unregenerate Part, <note place="margin">Rom. 7.22.23.</note> as was in <hi>Paul.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.3</note> Again, as a living Child, it always grown, tho' not in ſight, at leaſt in deſire and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, making a man more Conſcionable, and giving him better war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Sin; as a Clock is known to go true, when it ſtrikes right,
<pb n="237" facs="tcp:109796:124"/> tho' you cannot ſee it move forward. It gains by Opportunities, and waxes ſtronger by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Again, Saving Faith is known by its Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedents, and Conſequents, but more eaſily by its Fruits and Effects, than by its Cauſes; as Life, by Motion; and Fire, by Heat. <note place="margin">Gal. 5.6. Rom. 6.13.</note> And thus it is a living Faith. It loves and deſires the Word, Gods Ordinances, and all holy Means; becauſe it is both begotten, and, nouriſh'd thereby. <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.2.</note> It makes a new Creature, pruifying the Heart, and
<pb n="238" facs="tcp:109796:125"/> regulating the Life; <note place="margin">Acts 15.9. Rom 6.4.</note> It makes them Virtuous, Temperate, Patient, Godly, which before were the contrary; <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.5.</note> It works Repentance, and a true abandoning of Sin, making us grudge it any room in us. It makes one not content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Thinking he has it; but very deſirous, and induſtrious to be ſure, and Certain. It works Self-denial, both in regard of God, for doing or ſuffering h is Will: and of our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, in forgiving, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, and not doing them the leaſt Wrong,
<pb n="239" facs="tcp:109796:125"/> to do our Selves the greateſt Benefit; ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and deſiring his good, as it were our own; and requiting any hurt done us, by doing all the good we can. It drawn Virtue and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs from Chriſt, for the cure of our ſpiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. It makes us com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of much want in our Faith, and weakneſs in our believing, out of a Senſe of Unbelief, <note place="margin">Mar. 9.24.</note> as a burden to us; It convets more and more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Favour of God, and better aſſurance of it: therefore will make us neither to favour our
<pb n="240" facs="tcp:109796:126"/> ſelves in any Sin, nor to be content with any proſperity without it. <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.28. Cant. 8 14. Revel. 22.20.</note> It will make us long more after Chriſt, and his raviſhing ſweetneſs; as Lovers for the Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age day.</p>
               <p>It expels Worldlineſs from rulinginus; becauſe it finds an All-ſufficiency in Chriſt: So that we cannot love the World more than Grace, and Holineſs. <note place="margin">1 John. 5.4. and 2.16. Heb. 11.26. Rom 3.27.</note> It excludes Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of our Gifts, Parts, or good deeds; It works in us Inward, Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al life: Now Chriſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth in us, and we in him. <note place="margin">Gal, 2.20.</note> Which life may
<pb n="241" facs="tcp:109796:126"/> be known as natural life is, by the Working of the Heart, panting after God. <note place="margin">Pſal. 42.1.</note> And by the beating of the Pulſes in our regular motions of conſtant indeavours, and holy obedience; <note place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note> By the operation of the Senſes, diſcerning Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. By breathing a Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and ſweet breath of Grace.<note place="margin">Ecl. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> Col. 4 6.</note> By the motion of Hand and Foot, which moves to God, and for God.</p>
               <p>It drives out Hypocri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy, which ſerves not God for Love, but for By-ends. It will not ſuffer us to make haſt to
<pb n="242" facs="tcp:109796:127"/> depart from God, by evil means to help our ſelves. <note place="margin">Iſai. 28 16. Pſal. 40.1.</note> Laſtly, true Faith obtaines, what it believes, things for preſent, in preſent, and things to come, in their due time. <note place="margin">Matth. 8.13. and 21 22.</note> So alſo this Faith obtains all the Benefits by Chriſt: As deliverance from the Reigning power of Sin, Sanctification, and Grace, <note place="margin">Rom. 6.14.</note> as well as Salvation, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence on God, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, Contentedneſs, and ſufficiency in him. If we obtain theſe things, our Faith is True, or elſe it is Falſe and Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit: For how can we know that our believing
<pb n="243" facs="tcp:109796:127"/> Salvation ſhall bring us Salvation, when as our believing Sanctification does not made us Holy? Or how ſhall our Faith prove True for another World, that proves Falſe for this? But if our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Sanctification brings us This; then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly our believing our Salvation, will bring us at.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of Set Meditation.</head>
               <p>IN Set Mediation there are four things to be conſider'ds. The Circumſtances, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, the Act it ſelf,
<pb n="244" facs="tcp:109796:128"/> and the Concluſion.</p>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Circumſtances.</head>
                  <p>FOR the Time. This is left to every man's diſcretion; yet Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> adviſes us, to make choice of the Lords day in the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, when we may call to mind, what we have heard: and the better to keep it in memory, take the Hendi of Sermons.</p>
                  <p>For the Place; as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir'd as may be, and the room ſomewhat dark, that the Senſes may have no object to draw them away.</p>
                  <pb n="245" facs="tcp:109796:128"/>
                  <p>For the Space, there is requir'd but one hour in ſeven Days; and thou wilt find it the beſt hour, that ever thou did'ſt ſpend.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Preparation.</head>
                  <p>THE time allotted for this Exerciſe being come, retire into thy Cloſet, and having ſhut the door, before thou go about this great Work, do thy Homage; fall down proſtrate, grove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and kiſſing the duſt, laying thy ſelf at the feet of God, labor to be convinc'd of, and affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="246" facs="tcp:109796:129"/> with, the preſence of God; conſider whom tho art to deal with, a God before whom all things are Naked and Bare, who is in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Heavens, full of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Majeſty, who will not be dally'd with, or mock'd; but Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd in thoſe, that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach him: therefore muſt thou be careful not to ſpeak Fooliſhly before ſo Wiſe a God. Again, a moſt Juſt God; hat will not indure that you ſhould hide, or fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter any Sin: And yet of a moſt Gracious and marvellus ſweet nature;
<pb n="247" facs="tcp:109796:129"/> who, if we ask Pardon and Forgiveneſs, Grace and Wiſdom, confeſſing and forſaking our Sins, and hoping in his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, will not upbraid us with our Unthankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Undutifulneſs, Sins, and Rebellions againſt him.</p>
                  <p>Beg of God, aſſiſtance to perform this Duty; Pray to him, that He would be pleas'd to direct thee in the choice of thy Subject: that he would put ſuch Conſidedrations and Thoughts into thy Heart, that thou may'ſt be convinc'd of, and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with, the Truths of his Word.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <pb n="248" facs="tcp:109796:130"/>
                  <head>The Act it Self.</head>
                  <p>NOW pitch upon a Subject. The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our Meditations ſhould be ſuch things as are Plain, Certain, and Evident; and not Intricate, Abſtruſe, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſial, and Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Speculations; much leſs, ſuch as are Curious and Nice.</p>
                  <p>We muſt chuſe thoſe places of Scripture to Meditate on, as are moſt ſutable to our preſent condition, and the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, either in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
<pb n="249" facs="tcp:109796:130"/> or perſonal; to Our<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or to his Church.</p>
                  <p>Let your Meditation be upon Scriptures ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to your Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
                  <p>Let your Meditations be ſutable to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, you are to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of.</p>
                  <p>Let Chriſt be very much the Subject of your Meditation.</p>
                  <p>This Holy and Solemn Meditation conſiſts of Three parts. The firſt I call Conſideration; which is nothing elſe, but the convincing our hearts of ſeveral Truths, which do belong to the
<pb n="250" facs="tcp:109796:131"/> Subject whereof we Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate: To help us here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, we may conſider. 1 what Scripture, 2. what Reaſon, ſaith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it: a few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent Scriptures, and weighty Reaſons, are as good as many, for this purpoſe. We ſhould not over multiply our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations; but as ſoon as we find our Hearts ſtrongly affected, then we are to paſs over that part: but yet, we muſt be ſure to let our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations take deep root, before we paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver to Affections and Reſolutions; but in caſe
<pb n="251" facs="tcp:109796:131"/> our Affections are very much inflam'd, as ſoon as ever we begin our Conſiderations; we are to yield to the Inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God, and follow the leading of his Spirit, and not bind up, and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the extraordinary working of it; but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we muſt not leave blowing the Fire, as ſoon as ever it begins to flame, for green Wood will ſuddenly go out, unleſs it be very well kindled. We ſhould view the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in all its Faces, tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning it on all ſides; but not tye our ſelves up to Logical methods.</p>
                  <pb n="252" facs="tcp:109796:132"/>
                  <p>The ſecond thing in the Act it ſelf, is a Working on the Affections. The firſt, which is a calling to mind, and debating the matter, is an Act of the Underſtanding; the end of which is to inlighten the Mind with Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. The ſecond is an Act of the Will and Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, laying the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to heart, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it cloſe and home; the end of which is, to fill the heart with Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Here therefore we muſt examin Our ſelves, and Actions; whether they be according to the Rule, or wherein they
<pb n="253" facs="tcp:109796:132"/> come ſhort, or differ from it: Nor ſhould we give over this Search, till we find our Hearts in ſome meaſure become Pliable, Broken, and Affected.</p>
                  <p>The third part of the Act it ſelf, is Reſolution, to do this, or that. This Reſolution ſhould be firm and ſtrong, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, not future Tenſe; and as well againſt the Means, Occaſions, and Temptation to any Sin, as againſt the Sin it ſelf: We muſt peremptorily charge our Souls in every Faculty, Underſtanding, Will, and Affections, to
<pb n="254" facs="tcp:109796:133"/> Reform, and Conform to the Rule of God's Word.</p>
                  <p>In Meditating, we muſt joyn all theſe three toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, otherwiſe we ſhal ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bring our Meditation to any profitable iſſue; for if we only ſtudy to find out what's True or Falſe, Good or Evil, we may gain much Knowledge of the Head, little Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Heart: And if we only apply to our ſelves that, whereon we have muſed, we may, by finding our ſelves Tranſgreſſors, lay Guilt upon our Conſcience, without fruit or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. But if to both theſe
<pb n="255" facs="tcp:109796:133"/> we add a Reſolution, through Grace, to be ſuch as God commands us, and lay a peremptory charge upon our ſelves to live hereafter accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Law, and to follow his Counſel, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching what we ſhould believe and do, when we have offended him; then we ſhall reap both bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and comfort by this Exerciſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subsection">
                  <head>The Concluſion.</head>
                  <p>FOR the Concluſion of our Meditations, we muſt firſt with ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt deſire beg of God
<pb n="256" facs="tcp:109796:134"/> ſtrength, to perform whatſoever we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to do; being humble, and ſenſible of our own Infirmity.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, we muſt return praiſe and thanks to God, if we have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd any warmth of Love to God, or taſted of him, or any other Spiritual effect wrought in our hearts.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, we muſt humbly acknowledge our Failings in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of this Duty.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the Vows and Promiſes, which we have made.</p>
                  <pb n="257" facs="tcp:109796:134"/>
                  <p>Fifthly, we muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member what Paſſages in our Meditation did moſt affect us, and lay them up in our thoughts, that we may hereafter think upon them.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, we muſt by degrees warily go out of the preſence of God, being careful and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, that we loſe not the Senſe, and Feeling, Warmth, Strength, and Grace, we have got. This is the moſt proper and genuine Method for Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <pb n="258" facs="tcp:109796:135"/>
               <head>Preſervatives a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Sin.</head>
               <p>COnſider firſt the Fruits and Wages of Sin: The beſt, it yields, is Sorrow, and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if not dreadful Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments.</p>
               <p>If thou doſt commit it, t'will poiſon and inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom all Conditions: it will ſowre thy Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, with Preapprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of Wrath, haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thee, like an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate Creditor a wild Gallant, ſpoiling thy Jollity and Content. In thy Adverſity, it will
<pb n="259" facs="tcp:109796:135"/> add affliction to afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Superadding to thy outward troubles, a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving Soul.</p>
               <p>Beſides, Sin unquali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies thee for any good Duty, either to God, or Man: If thou pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, yet the ſenſe of Sin, thou bringeſt with thee, makes thee ungrateful to thy ſelf; and how can'ſt thou expect to be accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Holy God? In a good work, the Sin, thou art guilty of, makes the comfort of it Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pid: thy Heart tells thee, There is ſin in the Conſcience; and this makes thee aſham'd to
<pb n="260" facs="tcp:109796:136"/> own the good that is in the Action.</p>
               <p>Again, will it not be a grief to the good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, to be preſent, and Spectators of thy Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities? will it not work a loathing, and nauſeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them, and cauſe thoſe chaſt and pure Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who are employ'd for thy preſervation, to retire themſelves? And will it not be a moſt grateful Spectacle to the envious and malignant Spirits, and lay thee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen to their power and malice, who have gotten thee within their Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, unleſs God in
<pb n="261" facs="tcp:109796:136"/> mercy reſtrain them?</p>
               <p>Conſider the hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of the leaſt Sin. It is againſt God's Infinite Majeſty, and the riches of his Bounty, in giving his Son for us: Alſo againſt his Honor, and the Love, and Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty we profeſs to owe unto him, for all his Goodneſs and Mercy; and likewiſe againſt our Covenant with him: the vileneſs of which is ſeen in the fearful Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Sin of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, <hi>Adam,</hi> the old World, <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife, <hi>Saul;</hi> and ſo of <hi>Moſes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzah, David, Joſiah,</hi> and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="262" facs="tcp:109796:137"/> that inflicted on the Son of God, for our Sins. <note place="margin">Numb. 20.24. Deut. 3.26.</note> A Child of God cannot look to carry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the leaſt Sin againſt Knowledge and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence unpuniſh'd, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſpeedy ſubmiſſion and amendment.</p>
               <p>Live alwaies as in God's preſence, whoſe Eye is ever upon thee, and who may take thee away on a ſudden. <note place="margin">Gen. 17.1. Job. 32.22. 2 Cor. 5.15.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member thy appearance before him, and account every day, thy laſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing always prepar'd to give upthy Account.</p>
               <p>Keep continually a freſh remembrance of
<pb n="263" facs="tcp:109796:137"/> God's great Goodneſs; eſpecially his chief Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies Bodily and Spiritual, Ordinary and Extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary: Let thy great Deliverances never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of thy Heart; ſay always with <hi>Joſeph, How can I do this, and Sin againſt my good God? Gen.</hi> 39.9. <hi>Neh.</hi> 6.11,13. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.25. <hi>&amp;.</hi> 116.12.16.</p>
               <p>Walk ever painfully in thy ſpecial Calling, and in the Conſcionable uſe of all the meanes of Grace.</p>
               <p>Keep a perpetual me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of the former mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery of Sin, and
<pb n="264" facs="tcp:109796:138"/> Bleſſings of Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>Be reſolv'd to chuſe, rather to endure any miſery, than to Sin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God: as <hi>Joſeph, Daniel,</hi> and the three Children did. <hi>Dan.</hi> 1.8.</p>
               <p>Warily reſiſt the firſt motions to any Sin: <hi>James,</hi> 1.5. <hi>Luſt, when it has conceiv'd, brings forth Sin. Achan</hi> tells <hi>Joſhua,</hi> by what degrees he came to finiſh his Sin; <hi>Joſh.</hi> 7.21. <hi>I ſaw a Babyloniſh Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, then I coveted it, and took it, and it is hid in my Tent.</hi> Avoid eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry occaſion of Sin, as
<pb n="265" facs="tcp:109796:138"/> you would do of Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctious Diſeaſes. <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.22. Gen. 39.10. 1 Theſ. 5.17. Eph. 6.18.</note>
               </p>
               <p>But above all, uſe Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent Prayer, to be kept by theſe Preſervatives.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Of the Sabbath.</head>
               <p>REmember the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath before it come, that thou may'ſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch all thy own works in ſix days, to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the better upon the right Sanctification of the Sabbath. Meddle not with any Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Paſtime, or Ordinary Work, from <hi>Saturday</hi> night at eight of the Clock, till <hi>Monday</hi> morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="266" facs="tcp:109796:139"/>
                  <note place="margin">Iſa. 56.2,4,6. 58.13.14.</note> Now in thy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening Devotions allow thy ſelf ſo large a porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of time, as may ſerve for ſome preparatory Meditations and Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; and be not ſlight, and uncertain, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant to thy ſet times, and earneſt in this work: Now look into thy by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt Life, and chiefly to thy walking with God the laſt Week; be ſure to ſet all ſtrait between God and you; examine thy ſelf both by the Law and Goſpel, and ſee whether there be not ſome ſin or miſcarriage that lies unrepented of,
<pb n="267" facs="tcp:109796:139"/> which may blaſt thy next day's performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; if there be, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of it more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly in its aggravations and nature, reconcile thy ſelf with God by Faith, and Repentance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing thy Vows of walking more Conſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, after thou haſt cleanſed thy heart and hands. Let thy Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers be ſutable to thy Condition; beg fervent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forgiveneſs of thy particular ſins confeſſed and bewail'd, together with Grace for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture againſt them, and an increaſe of all other
<pb n="268" facs="tcp:109796:140"/> Graces, which thou ſtandeſt moſt in need of; eſpecially for a quiet, ſetled, compoſed mind, that thou may'ſt attend with all thy Soul upon thy holy concerns and buſineſs; likewiſe for inliven'd Affections, that thou may'ſt not be dull and heartleſs, but of a tender, and melting Spirit; for a pliable, and yielding mind, that thou may'ſt hear the Word with, and render the obedience of, Faith; that the Lord would fix thy mind, and make it ſerious, inlighten it, and open thy heart, that
<pb n="269" facs="tcp:109796:140"/> thou may'ſt have a clear and right underſtanding, that the Spirit would ſet in with the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Word, and make it effectual for the beating down of thy Corruptions, and that it may be the power of God to the ſalvation of thy ſoul: And laſtly, for the Miniſter, that the Lord would teach him what he ſhould teach the People, and direct and inable him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the mind of God, and make it manifeſt; that utterance may be given unto him, to ſpeak boldly, as he ought to
<pb n="270" facs="tcp:109796:141"/> ſpeak; and that God would Pardon his ſins and frailties.</p>
               <p>Earneſtly endeavour to taſt the ſweetneſs of holy Exerciſes, and to long for the enjoyment of God's Sabbaths; that ſo thou may'ſt come to make them thy De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
               <p>Riſe at leaſt three hours before morning Sermon, if it will ſtand with your Health, and not hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your fitneſs for Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Exerciſes through drouſineſs afterwards.</p>
               <p>When thou art up, retire into thy Cloſet; and having read two
<pb n="271" facs="tcp:109796:141"/> Chapters in the Bible, betake thy ſelf to Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation and Prayer. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with thy ſelf what an impure Sinner thou art, and into what an holy place thou goeſt, to appear before the moſt Holy God, who ſeeth thy Heart, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all the Sins of thy Life, tho' thou may'ſt have forgotten them, and hateth all Impurity and Hypocriſie: Now again examine thy ſelf, and Confeſs thy ſins un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, earneſtly pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the pardon and forgiveneſs of them, and ſo reconcile thy ſelf
<pb n="272" facs="tcp:109796:142"/> with God in Chriſt, and renew thy Vows to walk more Conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly; and eſpecially pray that thou may'ſt have Grace to hear God's Word with profit, and be inabled to Sanctify his holy Day, not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getting the Miniſter And after your private Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, read another Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Be preſent with the firſt at all Publick Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies of the Church, with cheerful Reverence, and the greateſt atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as before the Lord of the whole Earth: Both to declare thy Love and Honour, and for the
<pb n="273" facs="tcp:109796:142"/> good Example of others. Be afraid of the leaſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly geſture, or of being overtaken by ſleep, drowſineſs, or wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring thoughts. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12. Acts. 2.46. 4.32.</note> Joyn in with the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in every publick Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to due and holy Order, cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, with thy Heart.</p>
               <p>In hearing, apply each ſpeech, as ſpoken by God to thee in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: Like a Practiſer of the Art of Memory, refer all things to their proper place. If it be mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of comfort; this is for my ſick Bed, for my outward loſſes, for my
<pb n="274" facs="tcp:109796:143"/> drooping under afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for the Sence of any Spiritual Defection. If matter of Doctrine; that is for my ſettlement in ſuch a Truſt, for the conviction of ſuch an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, for my direction in ſuch a practiſe. If matter of Reproof, and threatnings againſt Sin, whether thy own or others, as a member of the ſame Body, or in danger thereof; be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, do not point at thy Neighbour, but deeply charge thy ſelf: This meets with my dead heartedneſs and ſecurity, with my Worldly mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs,
<pb n="275" facs="tcp:109796:143"/> Self-love, and Flattery of my own E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; This with my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable Cenſoriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with my fooliſh, proud Heart; That with my Hypocriſie, and the neglect of Gods Service and my Duty; That with my Irregular Life, and Converſation. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to walk in every good way, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from all evil.</p>
               <p>This is the beſt Art of Memory; for exceeding Joyes, Griefs, Hatred, or deſires, do leave the dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt Impreſſions in us, and ſo ſtick longeſt by us; In hearing therefore,
<pb n="276" facs="tcp:109796:144"/> labor to exerciſe Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity under Reproofs, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Thankfulneſs for Mercies, Deſire after Graces, and holy Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of amendment, and more cloſe walking, with God.</p>
               <p>As thou returneſt home, or when thou art entred into thy Houſe, Meditate a little while upon thoſe things thou haſt heard, and then kneeling down turn all into a Prayer; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don thy Sins of Worſhip, to accept of thee, and thy Imperfect perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances,
<pb n="277" facs="tcp:109796:144"/> in, and through Chriſt thy Lord; to give ſuch a bleſſing to thoſe things, which thou haſt heard, that they may be a direction to thy Life, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to thy Soul.</p>
               <p>Eat Moderately at Dinner; rather ſparing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, than plentifully, on this day: That thou may'ſt be fit for the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon Exerciſes.</p>
               <p>Som little and ſhort Diſcourſe about Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral things, upon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion may be ſo directed, and temper'd with Pious Meditation, as that it may rather be a furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
<pb n="278" facs="tcp:109796:145"/> than hindrance of the Duties of Religion: and indeed ſuch Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Diſcourſe, in ſuch a manner, doth not withdraw the Mind from God's Worſhip; But be ſure that in all thy Speeches and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons this day there be no lightneſs, nor Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor any thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming the Solemnity, Sacredneſs, and Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it.</p>
               <p>Walk half an hour af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Dinner, to digeſt thy meat; and then go to thy Chamber, and recollect what you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member of the forenoon Sermon.</p>
               <pb n="279" facs="tcp:109796:145"/>
               <p>If you are well, be ſure you attend on God's Ordinances Fore-noon and Afternoon: <note place="margin">Pſ. 92.1. Acts. 20.7.</note> For ſo often exerciſes of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Worſhip ought to be held.</p>
               <p>After evening Sermon, retire to thy Cloſet, read the Chapters in which the Texts were; then recollect and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine what you have heard, meditating on the whole Sermon in order</p>
               <p>The Coherence, and Explication of the Text,</p>
               <p>The occaſion and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
               <p>The chief Sum and Scope of the Holy Ghoſt in it.</p>
               <pb n="280" facs="tcp:109796:146"/>
               <p>The Diviſion or parts.</p>
               <p>The Doctrines ſeveral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by marking the Text, and how they were ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd out of it.</p>
               <p>The Proofs and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ſeveral Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
               <p>The Uſes.</p>
               <p>And laſtly, which is the chief of all, apply it to thy ſelf, and try what work every part hath in thee; If the Preacher's Method be too curious, or confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; then labor to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</p>
               <p>How many things he taught, which thou knoweſt not before, and be thankful.</p>
               <pb n="281" facs="tcp:109796:146"/>
               <p>What Sin he reprov'd, whereof thy Conſcience tells thee, thou art Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore muſt be confeſs'd, repented of, reſolv'd againſt, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended.</p>
               <p>What Virtues he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted to, which are not ſo perfect in thee; and therefore thou muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to practice them with more Zeal and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence.</p>
               <p>After the finiſhing of thy Cloſet exerciſe, or as a preparation to it, thou mayeſt walk in the Fields, and Meditate on the Works of God; for in every Creature thou
<pb n="282" facs="tcp:109796:147"/> may'ſt ſee the Wiſdom, Power, Goodneſs, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, and Juſtice of God: Pray to God, that he would open thy Eyes, ſo as thou mayeſt give him the Glory of his Works. Eſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider theſe things more fully in their ſeveral Ends and Uſes, as the Scriptures apply them. Be ſure to return ſo ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as neither thy Cloſet, nor Family Devotions (if not perform'd) be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted.</p>
               <p>Works of neceſſity may this day be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd, and works of Mercy thou art not to
<pb n="283" facs="tcp:109796:147"/> forget: Such as Viſiting the Sick, Inſtructing, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, Admoniſhing, Reproving, Comforting, Relieving, Collecting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To conclude, Thou may'ſt certainly expect that God will proportion his Bleſſings to thee, as thou meaſureſt to him in thy Preparation to come before him: <note place="margin">Lev. 10.3. 22.3. Ex. 19.22. Mal. 7.2. Mar. 4.14. Pſal. 44.5. Iſa. 56.58. Ez. 7.10. Gen. 35.2.5. Ec. 4.17. 1 Cor. 11.23.24. Mat. 5.23.24.</note> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as thou deſireſt the Bleſſing of a Sabbath, ſo reſolve by a conſtant Vow, to perform thy work of Preparation, and try whether the Lord will not perform his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe abundantly.</p>
               <pb n="284" facs="tcp:109796:148"/>
               <p>Examin thy Life, thou ſhalt find, that a ſtrict and diligent ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Duties of this day, has ever joyn'd to it a Bleſſing upon the reſt of thy time; and the Week that is ſo begun has been bleſſed and proſperous: Whereas when thou haſt been negligent of the Duties of this day, the reſt of thy Week has been unſucceſsful. I could eaſily, ſaith Judge <hi>Hales,</hi> make an Eſtimate of my ſucceſs in my own Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Employments, by the manner of my paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and ſpending the Lord's day.</p>
               <pb n="285" facs="tcp:109796:148"/>
               <p>On Wedneſday, or Thurſday evening, ſet ſome time apart for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>collecting and Review<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what thou did'ſt hear, and lay up in thy mind, the Lord's day paſt: this will rivet the Word the faſter in thy Memory, and put thee in mind to practice it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>A Prayer for the Morning.</head>
               <p>Q<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icken me, O Lord, that I may call upon thy Name: prepare my unprepared Heart, by the Bleſſed Influences of the Spirit of Grace and Supplication.</p>
               <pb n="286" facs="tcp:109796:149"/>
               <p>O moſt holy, and moſt glorious Lord God, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty Maker, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Preſerver of all thy Creatures, but eſpecially the Saviour and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fier of them that Believe, by the Merit and Efficacy of the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt; I, ſinful Duſt and Aſhes, dare not of my ſelf lift up my Eyes to Heaven, yet through thy dear Son, my, Saviour, come unto thee, according to thy Command and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, freely acknowledging that I am leſs than the leaſt of all thy Mercies, and therefore utterly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the ineſtimable
<pb n="287" facs="tcp:109796:149"/> favour of being thy Child, and a fellow Heir with Chriſt; that after ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a little here, I ſhould Reign with him for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: For thou know'ſt, O Lord, that in Sin I was conceiv'd and born, and that I have lived ever ſince in Iniquity: I am by Nature the Child of Wrath, a Vaſſal of Satan, an Enemy to Thee my God. It was thy great Mercy that I eſcaped thy Wrath, due unto me at the very inſtant of my Birth, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that Maſs of Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption which I brought with me from my Mother's Womb; and thy long-ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="288" facs="tcp:109796:150"/> Patience and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, that never fail, that I have not been long ago conſumed, ſwallowed up, or ſwept away, with ſome extraordinary Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for thoſe many groſs and heinous Sins of my Life: my whole Nature is deformed, with Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal corruption; my whole Life, my whole Life a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with the fruits thereof, all manner of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Tranſgreſſions. My <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding is full of Blindneſs, Vanity, and Infidelity; my Conſcience, Dead, and Remorſleſs; my Heart, Hard, and Impenitent; my Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="289" facs="tcp:109796:150"/> Diſorderly and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nruly and Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; my Appetite, Senſual, and Brutiſh: I have no ability to any good Duty; no reſtraint, or moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in Sinning againſt thee. Yea, if I do any Good, I am apt to blemiſh it with Self-love, and Hypocriſie; if I abſtain from any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, it is many times ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from the Act, than from the Love of it. I ought to have lived, as under covenant with thee, but, wretch that I am, I have broken my Vow, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſified my Faith, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. What Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="290" facs="tcp:109796:151"/> of thine is there, O Lord, I have not tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſed? What Grace, I have not abuſed? What Curſe, I have not deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? When I view the wretched courſe of my Life, and conſider my weighty and crying Sins, what, Lord, can I ſay? And what confuſion ſhould cover me? <note place="margin">Here confeſs to God thy ſecret Sins, with the Circumſtances of Time, Place, Perſon, and Manner, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> In how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things have I Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned againſt Knowledge, againſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, againſt Light, and againſt many Vows and Promiſes of better Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience!
<pb n="291" facs="tcp:109796:151"/> I have no colour of excuſe, nothing to plead with thee, in defence of my many, and heinous Sins: if I diſpute, I muſt lay my hand upon my mouth, and learn to abhor my ſelf in Duſt and Aſhes; for, Lord, for theſe my Sins I ſtand here guilty of thy Curſe, with all the Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of this Life, and that to come. But, O bleſſed Lord, thou art he, that Juſtifies the ungodly, and haſt ſent thy Son to die for Sinners, and haſt made a general Offer, and invited all to come unto Chriſt, that they may be ſav'd, whoſoever will, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="292" facs="tcp:109796:152"/> very one that thirſteth; yea, and haſt moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly promiſed, <note place="margin">John 6.37.</note> 
                  <hi>That him that cometh, ſhall not in any wiſe be repulſed, or caſt out;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">John 3.16,17. Luke 2.10.</note> and <hi>that whoſoever believeth, ſhall not periſh; that thou wilt not deſpiſe a broken heart.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 22.17. John 7.37. John 6.40. 2 Cor. 5.20. John 3.23</note> Nay, Lord, it is thy Will, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and Command, <hi>that I ſhould believe on the Name of thy Son, that ſo I may be ſaved.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 John 5.10.</note> And thy Word of Truth ſaith, That <hi>whoſoever believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, maketh thee a Lyar.</hi> O, Father of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, I am bold, in the name of Chriſt, to come
<pb n="293" facs="tcp:109796:152"/> unto thee, and by the hand of Faith to lay hold upon thy Promiſes; yet, feeling my own weakneſs, I beſeech thee ſtrengthen my unbelief: and what aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance I cannot have by my Faith, weakly em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing thee, let me have from thy ſelf, embracing me, who art mighty to ſave. Thou did'ſt inable thy Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant <hi>Jacob</hi> to lay hold on thee, and not let thee go, till thou had'ſt bleſſed him: Lord give me the ſame Strength, the ſame Courage, and the ſame Succeſs. I beſeech thee, O Lord, who deſpiſeſt not the ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a contrite heart,
<pb n="294" facs="tcp:109796:153"/> nor deſireſt the death of a penitent Sinner, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighteſt by thy Goodneſs to Reign, where Sins have moſt abounded, to pardon and forgive me all my Sins, and to waſh away the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>leanneſs of them, by that precious Blood of Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which Chriſt Jeſus my Saviour hath ſhed, I hope, for me. And ſeeing he has born the burden of the Curſe due for my Tranſgreſſions; deliver me, O Lord, both from my Sins, and thoſe Judgments, which hang over my head, as due unto me for the ſame: bury them in the Burial of Chriſt; that
<pb n="295" facs="tcp:109796:153"/> they may never have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to riſe up againſt me, to ſhame me in this life, or condemn me in that to come. And I beſeech thee, O Lord, not only to pardon the Guilt of my Sins, but to purge my heart by thy holy Spirit, from the Droſs of my natural Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; that I may feel thy Spirit more and more killing my sins, in the power and practiſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, eſpecially my ſpecial Sins and Corruptions. Let my Fleſh be Crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with its Affections and Luſts: And let me find the power of Chriſt's death, mortifying my cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions;
<pb n="296" facs="tcp:109796:154"/> and the power of his Reſurrection, rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing me up to newneſs of life. Arm me. O Lord, with the Furniture of thy Grace, and write thy Laws in my inward parts; that I may not only be thy Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, but thy Servant and Subject: Set up the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thy Kingdom in my Conſcience, ſubdue my heart to the obedience of thy Commands, win my Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to the Love of thy Statutes, conform my Life to the Rule of thy Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and transform me daily more and more into thy Image. Bleſs all the Means of Grace
<pb n="297" facs="tcp:109796:154"/> unto me, and me with a heart ſanctified, and ſet upon the Means, for the increaſe of Grace: let thy holy Word be my chief Treaſure, thy Statutes my Counſellors, thy Promiſes my Comforters, thy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments my Delicates, thy Sabbaths my beſt Daies, and thy Servants my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Companions. Renew daily with me the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of thy Peace; and now this morning, let thy Spirit from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Seal me a new Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of Mercy: that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to meet with thee in the ways and works of this day, I may be ſure
<pb n="298" facs="tcp:109796:155"/> to find thee as a reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Father, not as an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Judge. As thou do'ſt add Days unto my Life, ſo, good Lord, add Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and amendment unto my Days: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow a ſupply upon me of all thoſe Graces, which thou knoweſt to be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in me, and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for me; with an increaſe of all thoſe Gifts, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thou haſt already indowed me. Give unto me ſuch Spiritual Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight, that I may ſee thee in thy Word and Works: Let me live in thy ſight, and not without thee, as the Gentiles do. O, let
<pb n="299" facs="tcp:109796:155"/> me not be caſt out of thy preſence, as <hi>Cain;</hi> nor run againſt thee, as <hi>Balaam;</hi> but walk with thee, as <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noch, Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham:</hi> in all my ways taking knowledge of thy Preſence, Promiſes, and Providences. Bleſs me, O Lord, this day, in the Duties of my Calling; preſerve me from all fraudulent, oppreſſing, greedy Courſes: Draw my Affections from the Love of this World; fix my heart upon things above: if things ſucceed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my mind, make me thankful to thee, which haſt given the Bleſſing; if any Croſs comes, make
<pb n="300" facs="tcp:109796:156"/> me patient, and careful to profit by the Chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. good Lord, do thou bleſs me with ſuch a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Health, Peace, Proſperity, and every good thing, as may inable and make me Chearful in Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And becauſe the daily occaſions of danger to my Soul are infinite, teach me to keep my Heart with all diligence, to make a Covenant with my Eyes, to keep my mouth as with a Bridle, for the avoiding all filthy communication, to uſe ſuch words as may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Grace unto the hearers; to be ſober in Diet, wary in Diſports,
<pb n="301" facs="tcp:109796:156"/> moderate in Apparel, choice in my Company, and ever to practice that continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Fear, which has a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Bleſſing: eſpecially watching againſt thoſe Sins, I am moſt inclined to, and thoſe Temptations that are moſt likely to aſſault me. Plant in me Faith, without Preſumption; Love, without Diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Fear, without Infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity; Zeal, without Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſy; Knowledge, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Pride; Purity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Judging: Wiſdom, joyn'd with Simplicity; Courage, accompany'd with Meekneſs; Cheerfulneſs, with Sobriety; and let
<pb n="302" facs="tcp:109796:157"/> every Grace be graced with Humility. And be thou pleaſed ſo to bleſs all my Studies and Actions, that they may tend to thy Glory, the good of others, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of my own Soul, in that day when I ſhall make my final Accompt unto thee for them. O my God, keep thy Servant, that I do no Evil unto any man this Day; and ſuffer neither the Devil, nor his wicked Angels, nor any of his evil Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, or my malicious E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, to have any Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to do me any hurt or violence: But defend me from the Power, Malice,
<pb n="303" facs="tcp:109796:157"/> and Multitude of them all, both in my going out, and coming in, with the impregnable defence of thy Providence, and Guard of thy holy Angels, whom, thou haſt ſaid, ſhould to this end pitch their Tents about thoſe that fear thy Name: For in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thy Hands I do here, O Father, commend my Soul, Body, and all that I have, to be guided and protected by thee; being aſſured, That whatſoever thou takeſt into thy Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, cannot ſuffer any harm; ſeeing thou Ruleſt all things to thine own Glory, and the greateſt good of thy
<pb n="304" facs="tcp:109796:158"/> Children; and becauſe thou haſt aſſured me, that thus begging, I ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that I may ſet forth thy Glory, whereunto I do here bind my ſelf. And if at any time I ſhall this day forget thee, my God, I beſeeh thee, do thou in mercy remember me, and ſuffer not Sin to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me up, or grow ſtrong upon me, leſt I periſh. And now, may it pleaſe thee to receive at the hands of me, thy unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Servant, this my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of Praiſe and Thankſgiving, for all thy Mercies, both for my Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and Well-being;
<pb n="305" facs="tcp:109796:158"/> for the Means of Grace, and Hopes of Glory, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By thee at firſt I was fearfully and wonderfully made; thou did'ſt cover me in my Mothers Womb, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt me the ſhape of a Man, when it was free for thee to have equalled me with the baſeſt Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: Thou haſt made me Perfect in ſhape, and not a Monſter; Senſible, and of underſtanding, not a Fool: Thou didſt preſerve me in the Womb, nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd me, when I hung upon the Breaſts, provided means of Education, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me for an honeſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, and compaſſed
<pb n="306" facs="tcp:109796:159"/> me with many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Mercies, which others want. That I am now alive; that <hi>Satan</hi> has not had his will upon me; that I know the way, and the means, unto a better Life; that I have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and refreſhed the night paſt, when, for the Sins of the Day, thou migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt juſtly in the dead of ſleep have called for my Soul; and that I have dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly acceſs unto thy glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Preſence: Whence are all theſe, but from the freedom of thy Grace? If thou ſhouldeſt have given me my deſert, I ſhould have periſhed long ago.
<pb n="307" facs="tcp:109796:159"/> Father, I defire to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber with a thankful heart, all thy Mercies at any time beſtowed upon me, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued to me: My Health, Peace, Liberty, Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Credit, Fellowſhip, Succeſs in my Affairs, Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation from Dangers, delivery from Troubles, Recovery out of Sickneſs, Conſolation in Afflictions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But above all, for the magnifying thy Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to me, in the great work of Redemption and Salvation, by <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> for thy <hi>Chriſt,</hi> thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, thy Word, thy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, thy Sabbaths, and the Aſſemblies of thy Saints
<pb n="308" facs="tcp:109796:160"/> with all the helps of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, Inſtruction, Admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Fatherly Correct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, by which thou haſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to farther me in the way of my Salvation; yea, tho' my provocations have been ſo many, and ſo grievous, yet thy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions fail not, but are renew'd every Morning: For all thoſe Teſtimonies of thy Bounty, thy Pity, thy Patience towards me: I do, according to my po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty, offer up unto thee the Calves of my Lips, confeſſing thy Goodneſs, and the Due Service of my Soul and Body, as a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and reaſonable Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice.
<pb n="309" facs="tcp:109796:160"/> And now, O Lord, I come unto thee in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of thy whole Church and choſen People, and of all my Brethren, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they live upon the Face of the whole Earth: Defend them from the rage and Tyranny of the Devil, the World, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; give thy Goſpel a free and a joyful Paſſage through the World, for the Converſion of thoſe, that belong unto thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom. Judge <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Redeem <hi>Sion,</hi> in thy ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time: Call the uncalled, and perfect the called; raiſe up the Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, ſtrengthen the Weak,
<pb n="310" facs="tcp:109796:161"/> heal the Sick, relieve the Needy and Diſtreſſed,, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe ſuch as are in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint, comfort them that are Comfortleſs, either in Body, or Mind, eſpecially ſuch as mourn for Sin. Strengthen the Hands and Hearts of them, that ſtand in the juſt defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and Right; and confound every Adverſary, and Antichriſtian Power, and Policy: Eſpecially be favourable to all ſuch, a ſuffer any Trouble or Perſecution for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of thy Truth, and holy Goſpel; ſupport them under, and give them a gracious deliverance out
<pb n="311" facs="tcp:109796:161"/> of all their Troubles, which way it ſhall ſeem beſt to thy Wiſdom, for the Glory of thy Name, the further inlarging of thy Truth, and the increaſe of their Comfort and Conſolation: Give me a compaſſionate fellow feeling of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, others ſuffer; and prepare me for the day of Trial. Bleſs with all ſutable Mercies, this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, forgive the publick Sins, heal the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Calamities, and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes. Bleſs thy Servant <hi>Charles,</hi> our Sovereign, adorn him with all Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Graces, anſwerable to his high Eſtate; eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="312" facs="tcp:109796:162"/> with a Spirit of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Proſper the work of the Goſpel, and make thy Word to grow by the labours of thoſe, thou haſt appointed to the Service of the Church: give them Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency, Fidelity, and Succeſs in thy Buſineſs; Increaſe Wiſdom in our Counſellors; and ſtir up Magiſtrates, and men in Authority, to ſeek the advancement of thy Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and good of thy Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: contain the Subjects in their due obedience to Authority; bring to naught all Tumultuous and Rebellious Practices,
<pb n="313" facs="tcp:109796:162"/> Viſit all my Kindred, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, and acquaintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and all that are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to my charge, and whoſoever may claim an intereſt in this Duty at my hands, with ſuch Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings as they need: Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward a thouſand fold all, who have ſhown any kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to thy Servant; for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give, and have mercy upon all my Enemies, and let not one of them ever fare the worſe for any wrong done unto me. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, both to my ſelf and all that deſire to fear thy Name, grant all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, of Mercy and Peace in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> to whom,
<pb n="314" facs="tcp:109796:163"/> with thee, O Father, and the Eternal Spirit, be all Honor, Obedience, and Thankſgiving, throughout all Generations. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>Evening Prayer.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>O</hi> Lord God Almighty, the Great and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Being, before whom the Bleſſed and Glorious Angels cover their faces, thou art a God terrible in Wrath and Vengeance againſt all obſtinate wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men; but infinite in Mercy, and endleſs in Compaſſion, to all poor ſinners, that with unfeig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="315" facs="tcp:109796:163"/> Repentance truly turn unto thee: thou keepeſt Covenant and Mercy for ever, for all who deſire to fear thy great Name, and walk humbly before thee; I, Vile Earth and Aſhes, miſerable Creature, laden with Sin, might juſtly fear to lift up my Eyes to Heaven; but ſince thou art ſo far from deſpiſing and driving from thee a Weak, and Vile Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Wretch, as I am, that thou calleſt and draweſt ſuch unto thee, I am bold to approach the Throne of thy Grace, in the name of thy dear Son, my Lord Jeſus Chriſt, whom thou
<pb n="316" facs="tcp:109796:164"/> haſt given for Sinners, not only a Saviour, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo an Advocate and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, to put up our Suits, and make our Prayers accepted: Through him, Lord, admit me into thy Preſence, and hold forth unto me the Golden Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of thy Grace; let not thy Power diſmay, but ſtrengthen my Weakneſs; thy Glory not confound, but cover my Vileneſs; thy Purity not purſue, but purge my Wickedneſs. I can plead nothing but Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery in my ſelf to make way unto thy Mercy: from thee alone muſt all motives unto compaſſion be drawn;
<pb n="317" facs="tcp:109796:164"/> I beſeech thee, O Lord, be not aſhamed of my Poverty, be not weary of my Importunity; but as the Senſe of my miſery, leads me unto thee, ſo let the Pity and Commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſame, incline thy Merciful Heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me. I brought with me a World of Sin, into this thy World: I have derived from my firſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, not only the Guilt of their Sin, but alſo the Corruption of their Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; that Leproſy of <hi>Adam</hi> cleaves unto me, and has overſpread all the Powers and Parts both of Soul and Body;
<pb n="318" facs="tcp:109796:165"/> darkening, and miſlea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, benumming and abuſing my Conſcience, inthralling and hardening my Will, diſturbing and diſordering my Affections, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my Bodily Senſes and Members either as Porters to let in Sin, or as Inſtruments to execute it. And from this curſed Root have ſprung all thoſe Actual. Tranſgreſſions, which, in Imitation of <hi>Adam's</hi> Sin, I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and multiply'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy Majeſty, by breaking every one of thy Commands, in Thought, Word, and Deed; even
<pb n="319" facs="tcp:109796:165"/> from the beginning of my life unto this preſent time: So that there is ſcarce any Sin, but I have been guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of it, one time of my life or other; nay, this very day how miſerably have I departed from thee! how frequently and ſadly have I backſlid! in what Liberty have I allow'd my ſelf! how heedleſsly have I converſed! I have walked at a meer perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture with thee, my God. And here, O Lord, I deſire to confeſs, with ſhame, unto thee, not only the Sin of this Day, but thoſe great and notorious Offences of all my ſinful
<pb n="320" facs="tcp:109796:166"/> life paſt, with all thoſe heinous Circumſtances, whereby my Sins have been made out of meaſure ſinful: as the abuſe of thy Patience, the quenching thy Spirit, deſpiſing thy Goſpel, unthankfulneſs for thy Mercies, unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in thy Covenant. Theſe, and many more, are the Miſchiefs, with which my Nature is ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, my Life filled, my Conſcience hardned, and thy heavy Wrath moſt juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerved; yet, becauſe thou haſt, out of thy free Grace, given thy Son, <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt</hi> the Lord, a means of Propitiation, in
<pb n="321" facs="tcp:109796:166"/> whom thou reconcileſt the World to thy ſelf; I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beg of thee, through him, Grace and Pardon. O, let his ſufferings ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie thy Juſtice for all my Sins, and procure favour and forgiveneſs from thee; let thy <hi>Chriſt</hi> be my <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> to ſave and deliver me from wrath to come: And whereas thou haſt not only promiſed to deal thus with me, but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded me to believe that promiſe of thine; Lord I deſire to obey thy Command, and Seal to thy Truth; yet, privy to the weakneſs of my Faith, I pray thee help
<pb n="322" facs="tcp:109796:167"/> my unbelief: Behold not my Iniquities, O, Lord, as a ſevere Judge, to be avenged of them; but as a Sovereign: Phyſician, to cure, and heal them. Shew me my Pollutions by Sin, in the Glaſs of thy World, and by the Lamp thereof help me to ſearch and know how wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed I am; that Judging and condemning my ſelf, I may avoid thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and heavy Sentence; and may ſo hate, abhor, and be avenged of my ſelf, as that I may avoid thy Wrath and Puniſhment: O let Sin be as bitter to me in the attempting, as
<pb n="323" facs="tcp:109796:167"/> in the repenting; at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, more bitter in the repenting, than ever it was ſweet in the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. Grant me thy Grace to overcome my ſpecial Luſts; at leaſt, alwaies to ſtrive againſt them. Subdue my proud, haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and vain, Thoughts; and ſtraiten my crooked, and diſtorted Affections: Let me look on the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures and Profits of life, not only as thy liberal al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowances unto me, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo as <hi>Satan's</hi> Baits; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voiding all exceſs and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, and uſing them with thankfulneſs, moderation, and as things that muſt
<pb n="324" facs="tcp:109796:168"/> ſhortly leave me, or I them. Let me not value Pleaſure, Honor, Profit, Eaſe, or any thing what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever at ſo high a rate, as, for the love thereof, to make ſhipwrack of a good Conſcience: Let me meaſure my ſelf, not by what others Judge me, or I feel my ſelf to be; but by that I deſire, and labour to be. Teach me to keep a diligent account of what I receive from thee; remembring, there will be a day of Reckoning: and grant me ſo to manage, and employ thy Talents, that thou mayeſt receive thy own with advantage
<pb n="325" facs="tcp:109796:168"/> Let my whole Life be a preparation to Death: And the Meditation of Death, the Rule of my Life. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto my old and gray head, O Lord, forſake me not; and let thy Fear keep me from forſaking thee: let me be amongſt thoſe that are planted in thy Houſe, and flouriſh in thy Courts, who bring forth moſt fruit in their old age. Help me often to conſider the danger I ſtand in, through the Multitude, Power, and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty of my Spiritual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And to my Faith in thee, let me always joyn Fear; not only of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan,</hi>
                  <pb n="326" facs="tcp:109796:169"/> with whom I am continually to Fight, but alſo of the ſlippery paths of this ſinful World, and the Frailty and Treachery of my deceitful Heart, and Sinful Nature, ever running after <hi>Satan's</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements, and conſpiring, with him, my utter ruin. Let me ever remember, how <hi>Satan</hi> ſhews only the fair ſide of Sin, and choo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes the fitteſt Inſtruments to deceive, and knows, how to ſute his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: and alſo of the Scour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges which follow after Sin, the bitter Fruits thereof; how it unfits me for any Service, makes me miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb n="327" facs="tcp:109796:169"/> what ever my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be: And how thou wilt moſt certainly make thoſe that belong to thee, to feel the ſmart thereof, eſpecially if it be againſt Conſcience. Lord, let me never forget <hi>Satan's</hi> dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly malice againſt thy beſt Servants: how few of them have ever eſcaped to the end of their lives, without ſome grievous Wounds! Let me not, O Lord, be drowſy, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, in ſo extream dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; nor lulled aſleep, when I am even ready to be utterly ſwallow'd up: but let me ever be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring and buckling on my
<pb n="328" facs="tcp:109796:170"/> whole Armor, that I may ſtand faſt in this evil day, and preſerve my ſelf, until the Conqueſt be got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and I Crowned. O let me never deceive my ſelf, by imagining my caſe to be good, when I am but a Carnal Worldling, or meer Hypocrite; but, Lord, help me daily (but eſpecially before thy Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths) to examin and try my Spiritual Eſtate, how I grow in all Graces, in more ſincere obedience to all thy Commands, Faith in all thy Promiſes, and in the power of all true Godlineſs: That I may hereby not only avoid all
<pb n="329" facs="tcp:109796:170"/> Hardneſs of heart, Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, Sleeping in Sin, prevent an evil Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, with the dreadful Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments thereof, and be kept from Satans power; but alſo may get ſtrong Conſolation, may be every day more filled with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and delight in thee, increaſing in Love to thy Majeſty, People, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, in Zeal for thy Glory and Kingdom, full of Life and Cheerfulneſs in accompliſhing all thy good pleaſure, and ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſelf to thee only, and thy gracious direction in all things, having my Eyes and Faith fixed upon
<pb n="330" facs="tcp:109796:171"/> thee, believing thou wilt always watch over me for good, thy Fatherly care ſhall feed and ſupply all my wants, thy faithful and powerful Protection make me ſafe, and thy wiſe and holy Providence order all things for my advantage in the end. Save me, O Lord, from backſliding from thee after the manner of this evil Age, and preſerve me from all the cauſes thereof: conceited<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the goodneſs of my State; ſtanding at a ſtay in Religion; neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of any means of Grace, eſpecially the Word and Sacraments; unfaithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="331" facs="tcp:109796:171"/> in my Calling com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting, or living in, any known Sin, without ſpeedy Repentance. Grant me to Glorifie thee, according to my Knowledge of thee; and ſo to love, and practice thy Sacred Truth, that thou mayſt never leave me, or in judgment give me up to vile Affections, a Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate Sence, or the ſtrong deluſions of Anti-chriſt. And now, O Lord, as I am in duty bound, I do here preſent unto thee, from an humble heart, this my Evening Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Praiſe and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, for all thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Mercy to me, a poor miſerable Sinner;
<pb n="332" facs="tcp:109796:172"/> that I was born, and live in the ſhining Light of thy glorious Goſpel, and am not, as others, under the darkneſs of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and Tyranny of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt, in all Afflictions and Miſery: That I have any meaſure of Peace in my Spirit, when I might have been in continual horror of Conſcience for my Sins, and left unto the power of Satan; that thou haſt granted me health and ſufficiency of the things of this Life, many kind Friends about me, my good Name and Credit preſerved, and thy Bleſſings in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure upon my labours;
<pb n="333" facs="tcp:109796:172"/> whereas thou mighteſt have ſmitten me to have lain continually Bed rid, tormented with moſt loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome Diſeaſes and Sores, or, like a poor <hi>Lazar</hi> to have begged my Bread from door to door; yea, to have layn with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out in the Streets, or in Priſon, hungry, naked, thirſtie, (as many, better than my ſelf do) deſtitute of Friends, in the midſt of cruel enemies, odious to all, my Name rotten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and my labours ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed: and what is more than all this, that thou ſhouldſt continue all thoſe kindneſſes unto me, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfulneſs,
<pb n="334" facs="tcp:109796:173"/> great impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitency, and hardneſs of heart; and altho' I have profited ſo little by the means of Grace, thou haſt ſo long vouchſafed me, both of thy Word and Ordinances, thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Mercies; Fatherly Chaſtiſements, and Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, ſo that thou might'ſt in Juſtice have ſhut up all thy Loving kindneſs in heavy diſpleaſure, and have caſt me off, as one in whom thou takeſt no pleaſure; it is thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thy Goodneſs alone, which is the Fountain, whence all thoſe rich Mercies flow unto me. And that thou mayſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive
<pb n="335" facs="tcp:109796:173"/> all the Glory, ſhall be the conſtant Prayer and indeavour of thy Servant, all the daies of his life: to the which, I do here ſolemnly engage, and bind my ſelf in thy Sacred Preſence; beſeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee, to Sanctifie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me this night's reſt, that I be not troubled with any Terrors, or wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened with any Sickneſs, or impoveriſh'd by any Caſualities or Croſſes; but, that being defended un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Shadow of thy Wings, and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of thy holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, I may be ſecured both from the Aſſaults of Satan, and the deſigns of
<pb n="336" facs="tcp:109796:174"/> evil Men. Into thy holy Protection and Cuſtody, O Father, I do here com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend my ſelf, and all (that through thy Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs) do belong unto me: beſeeching thee, both to hear and grant theſe my Requeſts, and all other things needful either for my ſelf, or any Member of thy whole Church, for thy dear Son Jeſus Chriſt, my Lord and Saviour's ſake; to whom, with thy ſelf, and the Bleſſed Spirit, be all Honour and Obedience, from Generation to Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:109796:174"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
